<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony of the Light within. A glorious truth, which all the holy men of God did bear testimony unto, and from which they spoke forth the Sciptures, and the end of all preachings and writings was to bring to Light within, to worship God in spirit and truth, and to Christ within, the hope of glory. The truth cleared from scandals, and some of the errors and false doctrines of two Cornish teachers laid open and testified against. With a description of the true ministers of Christ, and of the free ministery both under the law and Gospell administration; ... Also a testimony of the dawning of the glorious day of the Lord, ... Here is likewise, in short, declared the differences between the old Covenant, ... &amp; the new covenant, ... Given forth from Christ the light within in love to the souls of all people, ... that they may have union with me in my fathers love ... whose name according to the flesh is Alexander Parker. Written chiefly to the inhabitants of the town and parish of Austell, in the county, of Cornwall, but may serve for any others who are in the same nature and condition with them.</title>
            <author>Parker, Alexander, 1628-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E909_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203124</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863196</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91119)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 137:E909[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony of the Light within. A glorious truth, which all the holy men of God did bear testimony unto, and from which they spoke forth the Sciptures, and the end of all preachings and writings was to bring to Light within, to worship God in spirit and truth, and to Christ within, the hope of glory. The truth cleared from scandals, and some of the errors and false doctrines of two Cornish teachers laid open and testified against. With a description of the true ministers of Christ, and of the free ministery both under the law and Gospell administration; ... Also a testimony of the dawning of the glorious day of the Lord, ... Here is likewise, in short, declared the differences between the old Covenant, ... &amp; the new covenant, ... Given forth from Christ the light within in love to the souls of all people, ... that they may have union with me in my fathers love ... whose name according to the flesh is Alexander Parker. Written chiefly to the inhabitants of the town and parish of Austell, in the county, of Cornwall, but may serve for any others who are in the same nature and condition with them.</title>
                  <author>Parker, Alexander, 1628-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert at the Black spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Two-page title, [A]1v-[A]2r.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Inner Light --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115383:1"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY OF THE LIGHT WITHIN.</p>
            <p>A glorious Truth, which all the Holy Men of God did bear teſtimony unto, and from which they ſpoke forth the Scriptures, and the end of all Preachings and Writings was to bring to Light within, to worſhip God in Spirit and Truth, and to Chriſt within, the hope of Glory.</p>
            <p>The Truth cleared from Scandals, and ſome of the Errors and falſe Doctrines of two Corniſh Teachers laid open and teſtified againſt.</p>
            <p>WITH A Deſcription of the true Miniſters of Chriſt, and of the free Miniſtery both under the Law and Goſpell Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; and how thoſe that preached for Hire and filthy Lucre, were teſtified againſt both by the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Nationall and Pariſh Teachers in <hi>England</hi> and elſe, where, who preach for Hire and ſet Maintenances, and ſue people at Law for Tythes and Maintenance, are clearly proved, by ſeverall Scripture examples, to be contrary to Law and Goſpel, both in Doctrine &amp; Practice, and in the ſteps and wayes of thoſe whom the true prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles teſtified againſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Alſo a teſtimony of the dawning of the glorious day of the Lord, and his appearing in power in the hearts of his people, which makes the world to wonder, and formall Profeſſors to rage and perſecute the appearance of Chriſt in power; with ſeverall Scripture Examples, ſhewing how the Lord ſent his Servants to teſtifie againſt ſuch who had the Form but not the Power of Truth. And how the Servants and Meſſengers of God in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages and generations who were in the Life and Power of Truth, were hated and perſecuted by thoſe who had the Form, but were not in the Life of Truth as they are now in this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
            <p>Here is likewiſe, in ſhort, declared the difference between the Old Covenant, where the Law, Temple, Sabbath, Circumciſion, and other Services were without, and yearly offering up Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſin, but did make nothing perfect; &amp; the new covenant, where the Law, and Spirit, and Circumciſion, and the life and and ſubſtance of the ſhadows are witneſſed within, and ſin and iniquity done away, and the bringing in of the better Hope known, which makes perfect, which is Chriſt within the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and hope of Glory.</p>
            <p>Alſo an Exhortation to all people to ceaſe from Man, and all their carnall and dead Obſervations without them, which doth not ſatisfie; and to turn their minds to the true light, and wait for the appearance of Chriſt within, who gives reſt and peace, and ſatisfies the hungry thirſting Soul.</p>
            <p>With a few words to thoſe Dear ones who are torn to ſee the deadneſs of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall profeſſion, who are waiting upon <hi>God,</hi> whoſe faces are turned Syon-wards.</p>
            <p>Given forth from Chriſt the light within in love to the ſouls of all people, who are groping in the dark without, that out of death and darkneſs they may be brought &amp; turned to the true light, that they may have union with me in my fathers love, who am redeemed and brought forth of <hi>Pharoah's</hi> Court, and do count it greater riches to ſuffer affliction with the deſpiſed people of God, rather than enioy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon. <hi>Whoſe Name according to the Fleſh is</hi> Alexander Parker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written chiefly to the Inhabitants of the Town and Pariſh of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell, <hi>in the County, of</hi> Cornwall, <hi>but may ſerve for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are in the ſame Nature and Condition with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>London printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115383:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115383:2"/>
            <head>To all You to whoſe Hands this ſhall come: OR, To whom ſoever it ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to, to read. AND To all in whoſe hearing it ſhall be read.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not that I deſire to be ſeen in Print, that was the cauſe of my writing of that which here doth follow, if otherwiſe, I might have been cleared. But thus it was, upon the ſixth day of the weeke, being the ſeventh day of the ninth month <hi>1656.</hi> there was a Lecture ſo called, at the Town of <hi>Auſtel</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and as I lay upon my bed in the morning of the day aforeſaid, the living power of the Lord did ariſe in
<pb facs="tcp:115383:3"/>me, and a great burden fell upon me, and waiting in the fear of God, where the ſecrets of the Lord are known, it was laid upon me to go to the Steeple-houſe at the place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and I knowing the terror of the Lord, durſt not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nor conſult, but gave up my ſelf in obedience to the Lord, and to his protection, though I knew the people to be a wicked gainſaying rebellious people; yet I knew him who limits and ſets bounds to the raging Sea, that it cannot paſſe its bounds, and my life being given up in the ſervice and work of the Lord, not fearing what man could do unto me in the power and dread of the Lord, I went to the Town, and ſo into the Meeting-place, where were two of the profeſſed Teachers, and in meekneſs and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience I waited (though under much burden of Spirit) untill the Prieſt had ended his confuſed, gathered in, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined ſtuffe: And afterward I ſtanding up to ſpeak, and to clear my Conſcience and the Truth from his Lies, and other things ſpoken at that time by him, both the Prieſts began to paſs away, and would not ſtay, though in the Name of the Lord I charged them to ſtay and anſwer, for I had ſome thing to ſpeak unto them, but notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, they would not ſtay, but went away, and left me amongst the rude and ungodly people, where, like rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wolves, they haled and punched both me and other of my friends that were there, that ſo it was I could not clear my Conſcience, nor eaſe me of that burden which was laid upon me concerning them, though much was ſpoken at that time, but little received: after a little time without much harm, I and my friends came away. But my burden was not taken off, though ſome of my friends (ſeeing their rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) perſwaded me to let them alone, and not to come any more amongst them. But on the firſt day of the week, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er our meeting was ended, I paſſed down to the Town with ſome friends, and having written to the Prieſt, after one Letter was burnt another was delivered to him, though at that time he would not read it, neither was very free to ſpeak with me. Yet notwithſtanding though there was little freedom, I paſſed to the Prieſts houſe, accompanied
<pb facs="tcp:115383:3"/>with one of my friends; where (coming to the houſe) I found them very light and ſcoffing, and little freedom I had to clear the Truth, though much was ſpoken, it was but like water caſt into the Sea. And after ſome little time I ſhaked off the duſt of my feet, as a teſtimony againſt them, and came away.</p>
            <p>But I was not eaſed of my burden, though I laboured to put it off, ſeeing I had been amongst them: but it lay ſtill upon me, and I waited on the Lord, and on the ſecond day of the week at night, lying on my Bed, I was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to write, and ſo in obedience to the Lord I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what was given to me, which here is committed to the view of the world. Read with a ſingle eye, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe Scriptures that I have ſet down both in the Margine and other places, and then try thoſe men whom you have long looked upon to be Miniſters of the Goſpell, and you may ſee them both in Doctrine and practice to be contrary to the Miniſters of God mentioned in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in the ſteps of the falſe Prophets and falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which the true Prophets of Chriſt and the Apoſtles teſtified againſt.</p>
            <p>That which I have written it is not in envy to any of their perſons; God is my record, it would rejoyce my heart that any one of them might turn from their wickedneſs, and unchriſtian practices, and ceaſe deceiving and making Merchandize of poor Souls, and lay down their Crowns at the Feet of Jeſus, and learn of him that their Souls might live; and though I be hated of them and others for my love in dealing plainly, not daring to ſpeak peace to the wicked whom the Lord hath not ſpoken peace to, but freely declaring the Truth as it is in Jeſus, owning the leaſt appearance of Truth in any where ever I ſee it, and cheriſh it; but do witneſs againſt all hypocriſie and outſide ſeeming holineſſe and hyocriticall Profeſſors, it is abomination to God, and the very prophane ones, and the Publicans ſhall enter the Kingdom before ſuch.</p>
            <p>I ſay, if I be hated for this my love in ſpeaking and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in plainneſs, not reſpecting any mans perſon, I have
<pb facs="tcp:115383:4"/>peace with God in what I have here written, which I value much more than all the deareſt love or greateſt hatred and frowns of men. So I do admoniſh all who read this (or any other) not to be haſty to judge, nor to ſpeake evill of things you know not, but receive in love what you can reach unto and ſee to be truth; and do not raſhly cenſure that to be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror which at preſent you do not well underſtand, but try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Tregangeeves</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Auſtell</hi> in the County of <hi>Cornwall</hi> 
                  <date>the 15. day of the 9. month, called <hi>November.</hi> 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Writen by one who is a lover of the Truth, and tenders all thoſe who love the Truth in ſincerity of heart, who wait for the appearance of Chriſt in Spirit, who am known to the world by the name of <hi>Alexander Parker.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115383:4"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony of the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, a glorious Truth, which all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men of God did bear Teſtimony un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and from which they ſpoke forth the Scriptures, and the end of all Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Writings, was to bring to Light within, to Worſhip God in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Truth, and to Chriſt within the hope of Glory.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O all you People in the Town and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Auſtel,</hi> young and old, high and low, rich and poor, Prieſts, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and prophane ones, of what ſort or degree ſoever, to you all am I moved of the Lord of Heaven and Earth to write, and clear my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whetheron will hear or forbear, but chiefly to you who are breathing and hungring after righteouſneſs in whom there are true deſires, and thirſtings after the Waters of Life, for you doth my Soul travail, and for your ſakes, (and the pure Truth which is daily ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by falſe and back-biting tongues) do I freely declare
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115383:5"/>and write theſe following lines, it being ſo the people of their Town and Pariſh; many of them being ſo rude and bruitiſh, that I cannot have liberty to ſpeak by word unto you, but they are ready to lay hands violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon me, and others of my dear friends, who in meekneſs and innocency have come amongſt you, they have been haled forth, and abuſed by the rude multitude; as I my ſelf was upon the ſixth day of the week being the ſeventh day of the ninth moth, (called <hi>November</hi> 1656) when I was in your publick meeting-place, and heard one of your Teachers whileſt he uttered forth the Divination of his own brain, that which by his ſtudy and labour he had compoſed and patched up, and ſo ſpoke forth his conceiving and imagination, and not the Word of God; Now I having heard, and having had ſome diſcourſe with your Teacher <hi>William <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcot,</hi> and another of his Coat, and being that divers reports, and many ſlanders are caſt upon me, and my friends, both by the Prieſts and others, as that I deny Chriſt, the Scriptures, Prayer, and the like, which things are falſe, and their accuſation I do deny; as to my own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, all their lies and ſlanders I do not value, they are as duſt under my feet, and I ſtand clear and innocent in the ſight of God and all juſt men, and their lies and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s doth not touch me at all, I know it is the portion of the Children of God to be reproached and reviled, ſcoffed, and ſcorned, this is but a fulfilling of Chriſts words, who was hated of the world, and perſecuted and put to death by the profeſſing People; and ſaith Chriſt as they have done unto me, ſo they will do unto you; if ye were of the world, the world would love you, but becauſe I have choſen you out of the world, therefore do they hate you, but bleſſed are ye when men revile you,
<note place="margin">Ioh: 15: 18, 19. Mat: 5: 11, 12.</note> and perſecute you, and ſhall ſpeak all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake, rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you, theſe Scriptures are fulfilled in theſe daies, upon this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115383:5"/>Generation; and truly I can rejoyce in all this, and count it joy, that I am counted worthy to ſuffer for my Lord and Maſters ſake, knowing this,
<note place="margin">Acts 5.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Tim. 3.12 Heb. 11 26.</note> that all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution, ſo their reproaches to me are great riches, and truly for my own part I ſhould be ſilent, and bear all theſe things pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently; But for the Truths ſake, and for their ſakes who are tender hearted I ſhall declare and lay open ſome of their Deceits and Errors, who profeſs themſelves to be your Teachers, I ſhall not ſpeak by hear-ſay from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but what I have ſeen and heard with my own eyes and ears, in tenderneſs and love to your Souls, and not in envy to their perſons,
<note place="margin">Rom 13.8. Mat. 5.44. Acts 13.14 15. Joh: 16: 2. Mat: 12:33. Jude 11. 1 John 3: 12, 15. 2 John 9. Acts 21. 27 28, 29, 30, 31. Luke 10: 3. Mat: 6: 5.</note> for I owe to no man any thing but love, my deſire is, that they might turn from their wickedneſs and live, and ſo I ſhall declare, and leave it to you, to conſider, and with the Light of Chriſt in your Conſciences, rightly to judge, <hi>John</hi> 7.24.</p>
            <p>According to the will of God, as I was moved by the living power, contrary to mans will, upon the ſixth day of the week, being their Lecture day ſo called, I came into the publick Meeting-place, (which you call a Church) in meekneſs and innocency, according to the practice of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and I ſate down, and imediately <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcot</hi> your profeſſed Teacher, ſeeing me, envy did ariſe in him, and the image of <hi>Cain</hi> did appear in his face, and he ſpoke to ſome of his hearers to put me forth; in this thing, if it were nothing elſe, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to try him, for the tree is known by his fruits, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy is a mark of the falſe Prophets, and they who live in envy, are of <hi>Cains</hi> generation and nature; and he that envies his brother is a murderer, and ſo of the Devil, and is no true Miniſter; and it was not the manner nor practice of the Apoſtles to cauſe any to be hailed forth, but on the contrary, the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt were haled forth and beaten, and abuſed, and in this age your Teachers are found contrary to the Miniſters of Chriſt, not guided by that meek and Lamb-like Spirit, that they were guided by; but he is plainly manifeſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115383:6"/>to have a contrary ſpirit of envy, and ſo the ſpirit of error, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>The ſame time one whoſe name is <hi>Halls,</hi> went up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the high place and ſtood praying there Phariſee-like, which Chriſt cryed woe unto ſuch that did ſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. and in his prayer he uttered forth his envy and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt Chriſt the Light, and prayed to his God, that they might not be guided by the Light within; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward prayed, that the Lord would reveal his Truth within: Now here all who are not wilfully blind may ſee his confuſion, and out of his own mouth I leave him to be judged, for Chriſt Jeſus is the Truth, and he is the Light,
<note place="margin">John 14.6. John 8.12.</note> and if the Truth muſt be revealed within, then the Light is within, and where this Light is manifeſt, it leads and guids all who are in it out of death and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all unrighteouſneſs, into the pure way of life; righteouſneſs and peace; as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>whoſoever follows me ſhall not abide in darkneſs but ſhall have the light of life:</hi> and all who deny the light within, denies the New-Covenant,
<note place="margin">Iſa: 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: 6. Jer: 31: 31. 1 Tim: 3: 9.16.</note> and the faith of Chriſt; nay further, they deny the whole Miſtery of Godlineſs, which is God manifeſt in fleſh; and this I ſhall prove by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that all they who deny to be guided by the light within, denies God, Chriſt, and the Spirit, which are all one in ſubſtance, though differing in names, for God is light, and Chriſt is light, and the Spirit is light, and they are all one God,
<note place="margin">1 John 5:7.</note> who is light, as <hi>John</hi> the beloved Diſciple declares, and this was his meſſage, <hi>that God is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all;</hi> as you may read <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5. And <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt declares and teſtifies of God dwelling within, as you may read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols, for ye are the Temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid,
<note place="margin">Rev: 21: 3.</note> I will dwel in them, and walk in them,</hi> &amp;c. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain read <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. <hi>There is one body and one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115383:6"/>who is above all, and through all, and in you all;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3: 10, 11.</note> (mind this well, <hi>In you all</hi>) Again read <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26, 27, 28. where <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the Miſtery which hath been h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d from ages and generations, but now is made manifeſt to his Saints, to whom God would make known what is the riches of the glory of this Miſtery among the Gentiles, <hi>which is Chrict in you the hope of glory:</hi> Again read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 16. <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you:</hi> And this is the New-Covenant of God, propheſied of by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> in the 31. Chap. 31, 32, 33, 34. which was not according to the old Covenant,
<note place="margin">Exod 34:1. Mal. 2:7. Heb: 10: 12</note> where the Law was written in Tables of Stone, and the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and they year by year offered up Sacrifice for ſin, &amp;c. <hi>But this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael, after thoſe dayes ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in the inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and will be their God, and they ſhall be my People; And they ſhall teach no more every man his Neighbour, and every man his Brother, ſaying, know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them, unto the greateſt of them, ſaith the Lord; for I will forgive their iniquity, and will remember their ſin no more:</hi> And again, read <hi>Luke</hi> 17.20, 21. <hi>And when he was demanded of the Phariſees, when the Kingdom of God ſhould come, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them</hi> (to wit Jeſus) <hi>and ſaid the Kingdom of God cometh not with obſervation, neither ſhall they ſay, lo here, or lo there</hi> (mark well) <hi>for behold th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdom of God is within you:</hi> Another Scripture I ſhall mention in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John</hi> 2.20, to the 28. <hi>Ye have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ction from the holy One, and ye know all things, &amp;c. Theſe things have I written unto you concerning them that ſeduce you, but the annoynting which ye have received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame annoynting teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no lie, and even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in him:</hi> Theſe Scriptures I have ſet down to prove, that he or they, that denies to be guided by the Light within,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115383:7"/>denies God,
<note place="margin">Tim. 32 26. Iohn 4: 23, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: Jer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: 31: 34. 1:27. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h: 16: 13 Job: 8: 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Joh: 5:29 1 Heb: 10: 16 Luke 17: 21 1 Jo: 2:27. 1 Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1: 3, 5</note> Chriſt, Spirit, and the Scriptures, and in a word, the whole Miſtery of Godlineſs, which is God manifeſt in fleſh; where the true Worſhip in Spirit and Truth is known and witneſſed, and the New-Covenant enjoyed, where ſin and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quity is done away, and blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the Lords remembrance; and this is light, within, which leads and guids all the Children of God, in the waies of righteouſneſs and peace; where the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and life of all figures and ſhaddows, and the life of all Scriptures is witneſſed and enjoyed within, for the Law is light, and it is within, and the Kingdome of God is light, and it is within, and the Spirit is light, and the Annointing, and Chriſt is light, and theſe are all one in ſubſtance; one God, who is a Spirit of light, and he dwells within his people, and as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8:14. and here you may ſee the error and blaſphemy of <hi>Halls,</hi> who prayed that they might not be guided by the light within;
<note place="margin">Jo: 17: 21: 23. Iſa 45: 13. John 6: 45. Ezek: 34:15</note> and in this he hath denied Father, Son, and Spirit, which are one God who is light, and is within, a guider and leader, and teacher of his People, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture Teſtimony, as I have mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And the ſaid <hi>Halls</hi> in his talk was ſpeaking of Anti-chriſt, and falſe Teachers, from that Scripture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18. <hi>Little Children it is the laſt time, and as you have heard that Anti-chriſt ſhall come, even now are there ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Anti-chriſts, whereby we know that it is the laſt time:</hi> Now I ſhall prove by Scripture and out of his own mouth,
<note place="margin">1 Jo: 2:22.</note> that he is one of the Anti-chriſts, that is againſt Chriſt, and denies him; read the 22. verſ. <hi>Who is a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar but he that denieth that Jeſus is the Chriſt, he is Anti-chriſt, that denies the Father and the Son:</hi> Now it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and proved by Scripture that he hath denied the Father and the Son,
<note place="margin">Iohn 10:30 Iohn 14:9, 10, 11 Rev: 21: 3.</note> who prayed that they might not be guided by the light within, for the Father and the Son are one, and they are light and dwelleth within; And again read another Scripture in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115383:7"/>Chap. 4.3. <hi>Every Spirit that confeſſeth not that Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God, and this is that spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Anti-chriſt whereof ye have heard that it ſhould come, and even now already it is in the world:</hi> Now to confeſs Chriſt come in fleſh at <hi>Ieruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> ſixteen hundred and od years ago, that the Pope doth confeſs, whom he ſaid was the Anti-chriſt, and this moſt in this Nation of the very prophaneſt ones, and many others do confeſs: But I do further ſay,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5: 11, 12. Col: 1: 27. 1 John 2: 22, 23.</note> that every particular man or woman that doth not confeſs Chriſt, but deny Chriſt come in their mortal fleſh, are Anti-chriſts, againſt Chriſt, and this <hi>Halls</hi> did deny, who denies to be guided by the light within, and ſo denies Chriſt within the hope of glory, and ſo is againſt Chriſt, Anti-chriſt.</p>
            <p>Further, the ſaid <hi>Halls</hi> ſaid, that Anti-chriſt was one that did oppoſe Chriſt, and this I ſhall turn back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own head, and prove him out of his own mouth to be againſt Chriſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ers work, which is for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Saints.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt Jeſus owned the Doctrine of Perfection, and ſaid in his Doctrin, <hi>Be ye perfect e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as your heavenly Father is perfect,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. and <hi>Halls</hi> ſaid that none can be perfect in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s life, and ſo opoſes Chriſt, manifeſting the ſpirit of Anti-chriſt.</p>
            <p>Several other things were ſpoken by him, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Chriſt and the pure Doctrin of Perfection, but theſe few that I have mentioned, are ſufficient to try &amp; prove his Spirit, onely one Scripture I ſhall mention, which he himſelf quoted to prove me and my friends to be falſe Prophets, which was <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. but read the 18. verſe and ſo on; where the Apoſtle ſpeaks of falſe Teachers, for ſaith he, <hi>many walk of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping that they are the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Croſs of Chriſt, whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is their belly, and whoſe glory is in their ſhame, who mind earthly things.</hi> Now whether this Scripture doth condemn them or us, I leave it to the honeſt hearted to judge; for as ſoon as he had ended his ſtuff, they both went away, and though I called after them, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115383:8"/>them to ſtay in the name of the Lord, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs both of them with ſpeed went to the Tavern, and there filled their bellies,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1:1, 2. Pſa: 145.20 Dan: 6:22.</note> and left me amongſt a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of bruits and heathen-like raging people, haling and pulling, and punching with their feet, had not the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Lord preſerved me and my friends, we might have been torn to pieces amongſt the raging and raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wolves,
<note place="margin">Mat: 10:10</note> and that day Chriſts words were fulfilled, who ſaid, <hi>I ſend you forth as Lambs in the midſt of Wolves:</hi> And this was plainly manifeſt, I came in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and was as a Lamb amongſt them, and they like ravenous Wolves went about to devour, but the Lord preſerved me and my friends out of their mouths, glory to his Name for evermore. Oh! how do theſe your Prieſts walk as Examples to the People, as the Miniſters of Chriſt did walk as Examples, and their converſation was in heaven, as you may read, <hi>Phil:</hi> 3: 17: 20. But theſe your Teachers their converſation is below, and if the people ſhould have followed them, they might have gone to the Tavern, and there filled their bellies, and ſit ſotting and drinking, which is a ſhame to hear tell of, which they glory in,
<note place="margin">Tit: 1: 16.</note> and are enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, though they profeſs him in words, yet in works they deny him; and they do mind earthly things, (as thoſe did which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of) for if it were not more for love of your earthly things, than it is in love to your ſouls, you would have fewer ſermons, for take away their maintenance and give them no money, and you will quickly know what they preach for; we have tryed them and found them ſo, and ſo do turn from them,
<note place="margin">Iſa: 2: 22.</note> and warn all others to ceaſe from man, and turn to the Lord, that he alone may teach you, according as he hath promiſed, and according as it is written, all the Children of the Lord, they ſhall be taught of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13.</p>
            <p>After I came from the Meeting-place, I writ to <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcot,</hi> and ſent it down to his houſe by one of my friends, who coming into his houſe, and asked for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115383:8"/>him, it was ſaid he was within: Then <hi>Vpcots</hi> wife came and asked what his meſſage was, and ſaid ſhe would deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it to her husband, and ſhe being earneſt to know, he told her he had a letter, and ſhe promiſed to deliver it to her ſaid husband; where, upon her word and promiſe, he gave her the Letter, but no ſooner ſhe had got the paper, not regarding her word and promiſe, did caſt the letter into the fire and burnt it: and ſo ſhe was proved a lyer, in ſaying ſhe would give it to her husband but did not, but caſt it into the fire, ſo ſhe manifeſted herſelf to be of the Divel, a lyer: and the Lake of Fire is the lyers por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as you may read <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee that the Prieſt and his wife are both of one Spirit, for ſhe made no conſcience of her wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds and promiſe: but I knowing their ſpirit, did keep a copy of the paper, which take as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>William Upcot,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SHew me an Example in the Scripture, where ever any of the Miniſters of Chriſt did command any of their Hearers to hale forth, or take away any that came in amongst them, as thou didſt this day to ſome of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, out of thy envious ſpirit, ſpoke unto them to take me away, becauſe I had my hat on my head, when thou thy ſelf hadſt a Cap on, and thy fellow-Prieſt, and ſeverall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that had their heads covered, and yet wouldſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and judge me for that which thou and others were guilty of, and ſo ſtirred up the people to do evill. O ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs man! It grieves my Spirit to ſee ſuch actions amongst you: Are theſe the fruits of thine and others Miniſtery, when in meekneſs and innocency as a Lamb I came among you (as that of God in thee ſhall one day witneſſe) thou thy ſelf who ſhould have been an example of good unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was the firſt that did appear in envie againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and went about to ſtir them up to cruelty and rage, and to hale me out of your Aſſembly when in innocency I ſtood and heard thy partner and brother in Iniquity untill
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115383:9"/>he had ended his frothy and airy lying ſtuff, as I ſhall prove by the ſeverall things was uttered by him, that he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the new Covenant, this by Scripture I ſhall clearly prove, and do charge him to be one of the Antichriſts that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, which ſhould come in the laſt time. And when I ſtood up to ſpeak, and to clear the truth from his lies and ſlanders, thou and he, like two hirelings, fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and when I called after you, and charged you to ſtand, yet you both went away, and left me among a company more like Dogs than Men, raging and ſwelling, haling, rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, punching with their feet, and ſo the Scripture is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled which Chriſt ſpoke,</hi> Behold I ſend you forth as Lambs in the midſt of Wolves. <hi>This was fulfilled this day in thy Aſſembly, who behaved themſelves like ſavage, wild and bruit Beaſts. And this is the nature and the image which thou haſt begotten them into: your fruits make you manifeſt to be no Chriſtians, but Brutes and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. In the cool of the day conſider, do not wilfully cloſe thine eye, nor ſtop thine ears, nor harden thy heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt pure innocent Truth, leſt God give thee up to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind. It is the ſame Jeſus as ever was, and the ſame Truth which thou and other do oppoſe. And ſurely, if thou doſt not with ſpeed repent, and turn to the Lord, utter darkneſſe will come upon thee, thy Talent ſhall be taken from thee, and into the pit of miſery ſhalt thou be turned, which is the portion of all envious, bitter, perſecuting ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. I have ſomething further to ſay unto thee and thy partner concerning his ſtuff delivered by him this day, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come up to</hi> Laurence Growdons, <hi>or elſe appoint ſome other convenient place where I and other of my friends may freely come, and as you are faithfull to your God fail not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Send me thy Anſwer by this Bearer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Auſtel <date>7. day of the 9. month 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>By a Servant of Jeſus, known to the world by the name of <hi>Alexander Parker.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115383:9"/>
            <p>On the firſt day of the Week in the evening I and my friend <hi>Laurence Growden,</hi> did paſſe down to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcots</hi> houſe, and coming in amongſt them,
<note place="margin">Ieer 23 31 Rom. 1 25. Iob 4:7:</note> I found them very light and vain, making a ſcoffe at what was ſpoken, and turning truth into a lye, but the Lord will plead the cauſe of the innocent. Then <hi>Vpcot</hi> accuſed me, and ſaid, I denied the Word, and I denied Prayer, and I denied the Sacraments: And my anſwer was, I own the Word, and I own Prayer, but the Sacraments I did deny there was no ſuch Scripture that ſpeaks of Sacraments. Then he ſaid, I did contemn the Ordinances, and that was becauſe I ſtood and ſate in the Steeple houſe with my head co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.3.</note> when as both the Prieſt and ſeverall of them that were there, had their heads covered, and yet would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me for that which they were guilty of: but as for keeping on my Hat in contempt, it is falſe: but for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake I could not bow to their Image, ſeeing their hypocriſie and diſſimulation, and feigned humility, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſhew of holineſſe outwardly unto men,
<note place="margin">Prov. 15 8. Iſai 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ier: 6, 20</note> when they are full of hypocriſie and ſin within, the Prayers &amp; Sacrifices of ſuch arean abomination to the Lord. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I having ſome diſcourſe with <hi>Halls,</hi> about ſomething ſpoken by him, he not being able to ſtand before the Truth, he would have ſhuffled off, and ſaid, not onely by the light within, and would have put in that word <hi>onely,</hi> which was not ſpoken by him in the Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe; but his words were plainly proved, that they might not be guided by the light within. He affirmed likewiſe that the Scriptures were the rule of life, and the way to ſalvation, and the will and mind of God. All which things I anſwered to at that time, and owned the Scriptures to be a Teſtimony and an outward declartion of all theſe, the rule of life, and the way to ſalvation, and the will and mind of God; but the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are not the Rule of Life, nor the way to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, nor the will and mind of God, which I ſhall prove by Scripture. There is but one Rule of life, and that is the Spirit of God which is life, and gives life, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115383:10"/>makes free from the Law of Sin and Death; and this is the Comforter which guides and leads into all truth:
<note place="margin">Iohn 14 26, &amp; 15, 13. Iohn 6.61. 2 Cor. 3 6. Rom. 8, 2. 1 Cor. 2.11.</note> All who obey and give up to be guided by it, which the world cannot receive. But there is no life in the Scriptures, it is a dead Letter, and none can underſtand it but as they are led and guided by the quickning Spirit: For though Chriſt bid the Jewes ſearch the Scripture, he doth not ſay there is life in them, or that they were the Rule of Life, though they thought to have eternall life in them; but they would not come to Chriſt that they might have life,
<note place="margin">Iohn 5 39 40 Iohn 14.6: Iohn 1.4. 2 Pet. 1.21, 22. Heb. 13 8. Acts 14.12. 1 Cor. 2.16. Acts 4.32.</note> who was the life, and his life is the light of men, and this Life, and Light, and Rule was within the holy Men, who ſpoke forth the Scripture, and the rule of life is the ſame now, which is ſpirituall within, which the Scripture declares of, but is not it. Secondly, the way to ſalvation is but one, which is Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> and there is <hi>no man can come to the Father but by me;</hi> but the Scriptures are not Chriſt, ſo not the way to ſalvation, but a teſtimony of the way. Thirdly, the mind of God is pure and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and was within the holy men that gave forth the Scriptures, and they were all of one minde: but there are many that have the Scriptures, but have not the mind of God, neither are they all of one mind, but many minds, and many opinions, and their minds are earthly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: ſo I ſay, That, which a man may have, and not have the mind of God, is not the mind of God: but a man may have the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Luke 1.1. 1 Iohn 5.10.</note> and not have the mind of God; ſo the Scriptures are not it; but a declaration of it, and ſo I own them, and bear teſtimony unto the ſame Truth, that the Scriptures bear teſtimony unto, and have the witneſs within my ſelf according to Scripture teſtimony, <hi>He that believes hath the witneſs in himſelf.</hi> And the ſaid <hi>Halls</hi> being asked if he knew God, and he made a ſcoff at it becauſe ſuch a queſtion was propounded to him, and he ſaid he knew God: and I asked him if he kept the Commandements, he ſaid, No Now try him by the Scriptures and we ſhall find him to be a lyer; read 1 <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115383:10"/>2, 3, 4 <hi>verſes,</hi> Hereby do we know that we know God, if we keep his Commandements. He that ſaith, I know God and keepeth not his Commandements, is a lyar,
<note place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> and the Truth is not in him. And here out of his own mouth he is proved by Scripture to be a lyar, and ſo no Miniſter of Chriſt. Then he propounded the ſame queſtion unto me, whether I knew God and kept his commandments,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.30. 1 Iohn 5.3. Pſal. 119.143</note> which things I anſwered, and witneſſed to truth, being made able by the power and life of Chriſt dwelling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, by whom all things are made eaſie, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements are not grievous but joyous, they are my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Then he ſaid, there was none perfect in this life, therefore none can keep the commandements of God. But his firſt thing I deny, and it is falſe, as I ſhall prove by Scripture. Read <hi>Job</hi> 1.8. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Satan, Haſt thou conſidered my ſervant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God and eſcheweth evill.</hi> Here you may ſee the Lords own teſtimony, and he that ſaith there is none per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this life, is a blaſphemer,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 37.37<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Cor. 2.6. Col. 4.12. Phil. 3.15.</note> who would make God a lyar. And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Mark the perfect and the upright man, for the end of that man is peace.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>We preach wiſdom amongst them that are perfect.</hi> And again, one prayeth in another place, That they might ſtand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and compleat in all the will of God; <hi>And let us, as many as are perfect, be thus minded.</hi> Here are many Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that witneſs the truth of Chriſts pure Doctrine of perfection. <hi>For if any be in Chriſt he is a new creature,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.17. Phil. 5.24.</note> old things are paſſed away, and all things are become new,</hi> and <hi>they that are Chriſts, have crucified the fleſh with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and luſts.</hi> Then wo to all them that live in ſin, and plead for ſin while they walk on the earth, they be enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 3.11. 1 Cor. 6 9. 10 Iohn 3, 8. Heb. 11.14. Eph. 5.27. Luke 1.74, 75 1 Iohn 3.8.</note> and deny the end of Chriſts coming, who came to take away ſin, and to pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rifie the heart, and purge the conſcience from dead works, that his people may be a holy people to ſerve the Lord in purity &amp; holineſs of life For, for this purpoſe was the Son of God made manifeſt, that he might deſtroy the works of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115383:11"/>the Divel; and all ſin is a work of the Divel, and defiles the Temple,
<note place="margin">Iſai: 51.2. Iſai. 48.22 Maark 7.22, Eph: 2, 12, Iohn 8, 34, 44 Iſai: 1, 17, Mat. 11, 28, 29</note> and ſeparates from God, and breaks the peace with God; and there neither is nor can be any reconciliation to God, untill there be a ſeparation from ſin: For all who live in ſin, profeſs what they will, they are enemies to God, and ſtrangers from the covenant of promiſe, and are of their Father the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, who is the author of all ſin and unrighteouſneſs, therefore ceaſe from ſin, and learn to do well, that you may live and enjoy reſt and peace.</p>
            <p>Now whereas it is ſaid in one place of Scripture,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 1, 8 Heb: 10, 16, 17, 18, 1 Iohn 3, 9,</note> 
               <hi>If we ſay we have no ſin we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us.</hi> This is the refuge for all the Divels Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and ſervants to flye unto, who live in ſin in the old nature, and in the unconverted ſtate, to plead againſt the new Covenant and new Birth, where ſin and iniquity is done away. And this Scripture did Prieſt <hi>Halls</hi> bring to maintain his argument againſt perſecution. Then I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced another Scripture in the ſame Epiſtle of <hi>John, chap.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin becauſe he is born of God.</hi> And this he would give a meaning to, and I told him,
<note place="margin">2 Pet 1, 20,</note> the Scriptures were of no private inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation. An he asked me how I would reconcile thoſe two Scriptures: &amp; I told him I owned them as they were ſet down, for they were ſpoken to ſeverall conditions. And then he began to boaſt, and would have turned the truth which was ſpoken by me into a lie, and ſaid I ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Scriptures as they are, and then takes them upon condition; and thus impudently ſtood in a lye, and after I ſpoke my former words and told him, the Scriptures were ſpoken to ſeverall conditions, and inſtanced ſome Scriptures to prove it, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle declares how he was ſent forth, and to what end, which was to open the blind eyes, and to turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, that they might receive forgiveneſs of ſins, &amp;c. Here you may ſee they were in a condition of ſin, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115383:11"/>Again, read 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.12. where the Apoſtle writes to them whoſe ſins were forgiven,
<note place="margin">Col: 2, 13,</note> 
               <hi>I Write unto you little Children, becauſe your ſinnes are forgiven you.</hi> Here you may ſee another condition. Again, read <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. <hi>And you being dead in your ſins, and the uncircumciſion of your fleſh, hath he quickned together with him,
<note place="margin">Rom: 9, 20, Rom: 6, 22, 1 Cor: 15, 49, 1 Cor: 15, 22, Eph: 2, 1, 2, 3, 1 Pet. 1, 23. 1 Iohn 5, 18, 1 Iohn 3. 6, 7, 8, Gal: 6, 7, Mat: 7, 21, Rom. 8.13,</note> having forgiven you all treſpaſſes.</hi> Here again, as your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings comes to be opened, you may ſee the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and times they were in, to whom the Scriptures were written, there was a time when they were dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins; and there was a time when they were quickned, and their ſins were forgiven them. And there was a time when they were the ſervants of Sin, and free from Righteouſneſs; and there was a time when they were free from ſin, and become ſervants of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. There is the firſt man and the ſecond man, <hi>The firſt Man is of the earth earthly, and the ſecond Man is the Lord from heaven.</hi> There is the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam;</hi> In the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> all die, and are dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, and they who be there in that ſtate, are full of ſin, and if they or any of them ſhould ſay they have no ſin, they deceive themſelves, and the truth is not in them; but all who are born again of the immortall ſeed, are kept by the power of God, and the wicked one toucheth them not, for whoſoever abides in Chriſt doth not commit ſin, for whoſoever ſinneth hath not ſeen him neither known him; he that doth righteouſnes is of God, and he that doth commit ſin is of the Div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll: therefore be not deceived, for God will not be mocked with your words, it is not your ſaying, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> nor your cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary worſhip, and outſide ſeeming holineſs, it will not cover your nakednes, nor bring peace to your ſouls, as long as you live in ſin, for if yee live after the fleſh, yee ſhal die, and reap corruption, but if ye through the Spirit do mortifie the deeds of the body, then ſhall yee live. But ſome whoſe eyes are blinded by the God of this world, ſtumble becauſe it is ſaid <hi>If (We) ſay,</hi> &amp;c. the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle takes in himſelf. Now this I ſay, That the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115383:12"/>Apoſtles many times do come down to the capacities of others when they themſelves have paſſed through ſuch conditions. As for example, <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle in the third chapter of his Epiſtle, ſpeaking of the unrulineſs of the tongue, though it is but a little, yet it is an unruly member full of deadly poyſon, therewith bleſs we God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Father, &amp; therewith curſ we men which are made after the ſimilitude of God. Here we may ſee <hi>James</hi> ſaid <hi>(We)</hi> but he himſelf was no curſer, but redeemed from it, and this I inſtanced to <hi>Halls,</hi> and them preſent at that time, and he ſaid though he was not one, he had been a curſer, and I told him, ſo had <hi>Iohn</hi> been a ſinner, and ſo have we all ſinned, and if we ſay we have not ſinned, we make him a lyar:
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.9, 10.</note> But if we confeſſe our ſins, he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs. Mark, he doth not ſay <hi>from part,</hi> but <hi>from all ſins;</hi> for if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from <hi>all ſin,</hi> and they who deny the light within, and deny the freedom from ſin, deny Chriſt and the end of his coming, and would make his blood of none effect: and freely from the Lord do I teſtifie againſt all ſuch as Miniſters of Anti-chriſt, and they have made a Covenant with Hell and Death, and no longer time will ſerve, but term of life; they tell people they muſt live in ſin, and never be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin while they live, and flatter them with a vain hope of going to heaven, when there is but this hope, which doth not purifie their hearts, is <hi>the hope of the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 28.15. Iob 8 13, &amp; 11.20 Mat. 15.30.</note> which ſhall periſh, and their end will be wo and utter darkneſs,</hi> the portion of all ſuch who live in their ſins: Therefore fear the Lord, and let every one that nameth the name of Jeſus Chriſt, depart from iniquity, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 19.</p>
            <p>Further, the ſame time <hi>Will. Vpcot</hi> affirmed, that there was no Miniſters of the Spirit now: which thing I did deny,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 50.2. Heb. 13 8.</note> and do affirm it to be falſe; for God is the ſame now as formerly, and Jeſus Chriſt is the ſame to day as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115383:12"/>yeſterday, and the ſpirit is the ſame; and all who are made Miniſters by the will of God,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.6. 2 Cor. 2.4. 1 Cor. 5, 19. Iſal. 61,2.</note> are Miniſters of the Spirit and of power, and declare the word of life and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, and miniſters peace and glad tydings to impriſoned ſouls; and condemnation, and the day of vengeance upon all Oppreſſors which keeps the Seed in bondage.</p>
            <p>He further ſaid, that <hi>Paul</hi> was not a Miniſter of the Spirit, which thing is likewiſe falſe and a lie, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to affirm: read 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. and there you may read the Apoſtles Teſtimony, where he ſaith, <hi>Who alſo hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit.</hi> Here it is evidently mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that <hi>Paul</hi> was a Miniſter of the Spirit; therefore all that ſay he was not, are lyars,
<note place="margin">Iohn 8.44. Rev, 21.18.</note> but <hi>William <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcot</hi> did ſay that <hi>Paul</hi> was not a Miniſter of the Spirit; therefore he is a lyar, and ſo of the Devil; let the Scripture be a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt him.</p>
            <p>Further he the ſaid <hi>William <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcot</hi> ſaid, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were the Goſpel, and I asked him what part, and he ſaid the New Teſtament, <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and the Epiſtles; and he ſaid further, that all the whole Scripture was the Goſpel: All which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the Scriptures are but the report,
<note place="margin">Luke 1.1.</note> and fame of the Goſpel, but not the Goſpel, for the Goſpel is a Miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and cannot be bought for money; but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which is a declaration, may be bought for a ſmal ſum of money, therefore not the Goſpel; for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is the power of God unto ſalvation, unto every one that doth believe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>For therein is the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God revealed from faith to faith, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the juſt ſhall live by faith; for the wrath of God is revealed from heaven, againſt all ungodlineſs and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs, becauſe that which may be known of God is manifeſt in them, for God hath ſhewed it unto them,</hi> verſe 17, 18, 19. The Goſpel is <hi>glad tydings</hi> to captive and weary ſouls, which thoſe that preached the Goſpel did witneſs the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115383:13"/>of,
<note place="margin">Iſa: 51: 1, 2. Rom: 3.24. Epheſ. 1: 7.</note> and the bonds of iniquity was broken, and the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ſet free, and this Goſpel, the power of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation, was in the beginning before all time, and was manifeſt in the holy men of God, from which the Scriptures were declared and ſpoken forth; and they are a declaration of the Goſpel, the power of God unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but they are not the Goſpel, the power of God unto ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Several other things was ſpoken at that time, but theſe are ſufficient that I have here ſet down, to all who love their ſouls and are not wilfully blind, to try their ſpirits, to be contrary to the ſpirit of truth, and ſo to be turned away from, as the Miniſters of Chriſt exhorts, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. &amp;c. and to them I did ſpeak, and warn them to give over deceiving of the people, and told them the judgements of God would come upon them,
<note place="margin">Mat: 10.14.</note> and ſhaked off the duſt of my feet, as a teſtimony againſt them, and came away; being ſeveral times bidden go forth, and threatned to be put forth; and ſome that was in the of the houſe of the ruder ſort,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ: 1: 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> did threaten miſchief againſt me, but neither of the Prieſts, nor any other did reprove them for it, but did encourage them rather in their wickedneſs, but the Lord God of power is now appearing, and will render vengeance in flames of fire, upon all that know not God,
<note place="margin">Pſal: 111: 2, 3 Rom: 11.33. Rom: 1: 21: to the end.</note> and that do not obey the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, when he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to be admired in all them that believe, read 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 10. and truly his work is wonderful and marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in our eyes, his waies are paſt finding out by any worldy wit or wiſdom, as it is written, the world by wiſdom knows not God, for the preaching of the Croſs of Chriſt is fooliſhneſs to worldly, wiſe, and Scripture-learned ones; but unto all that believe both Jews and Gentiles, Chriſt the power of God, and the wiſdom of God, becauſe the fooliſhneſs of. God is wiſer than men, and the weakneſs of God is ſtronger than men; for ſaith
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115383:13"/>the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye ſee your calling brethren, how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble, are called; but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weak things of the world, to confound the things which are mighty, and baſe things of the world, and things that are deſpiſed, hath God choſen, yea and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus the beloved ſon of God, when he choſe himſelf diſciples and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, he did not chooſe them by their greatneſs in the world, nor by their great learning, and Scripture know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; he did not chooſe him diſciples of the great Doctors and learned Rabbies of thoſe times, neither of the Rulers nor chief of the people; and this made the Rulers and chief Prieſts to rage and deſpiſe, and called him a Carpenter,
<note place="margin">Mark 6: 3. Jo: 7: 48, 49. Mat: 26: 3, 4. Acts 4: 13. Mat: 4: 18, 21.</note> and thoſe that followed him a curſed people that knew not the Law, and the Rulers and chief Prieſts took counſel againſt Chriſt to put him to death, ſuch as were of great eſteem in the world he did not chooſe, but he chooſed ignorant and unlearned men, and deſpiſed ones in the worlds account, many of them Fiſher men, ſuch did Chriſt make-choice of,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2 cha.</note> that the power might be of God, and not of man, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence, but he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord. And when <hi>Paul</hi> came to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> he came not with excellency of ſpeech or of wiſdom declaring unto them the teſtimony of God, for ſaith he, I determined not to know any thing amongſt you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified, and I was with you in weakneſs and in fear, and in much trembling; but now trembling is deſpiſed, and made a mock and a ſcoff at in your Towns, ſtreets, and villages, and moſt places, the Children of God, who fear God and tremble at his word, are made a mock and a by-word, under the name of <hi>Quakers;</hi> it is become their Table talk, and at their Ale-houſes and Taverns, and indeed moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they come; the children of God are become the reproach, and as a by-word amongſt them, every
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115383:14"/>one giving their cenſures,
<note place="margin">Jer: 6: 10. Mat: 10: 22. Jam: 3: 15.</note> one crying one thing, another crying another thing, and all are in confuſion; but theſe are them whom the Lord doth love and regard, who tremble at his word, as it is written in the prophets; <hi>Heaven is my Throne,
<note place="margin">Iſa: 66: 1, 2.</note> and Earth is my footſtool, what houſe will ye build unto me ſaith the Lord? or what is the place of my reſt? hath not my hand made all theſe things? and all theſe things have been, ſaith the Lord, but to this man will I look to, and regard, he that is of a meek and a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word.</hi> But ſuch are now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, and beaten, and whipped and ſtocked, and ſent up and down the Country as Vagabonds,
<note place="margin">Prov. 19: 29. Prov: 10 6, 7. Phil: 2: 12.</note> and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſent to priſon; but God will plead the cauſe of the innocent, and the ſcoffers and ſcorners he will judge, and bleſs and preſerve them that love righteouſneſs, that work out their ſalvation with fear and trembling. And further <hi>Paul</hi> declares that his ſpeech, and his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was not with enticing words of mans wiſdome, but in demonſtration of the ſpirit and of power, that their faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdome of men, but in the power of God; howbeit (ſaith he) we ſpeak wiſdome amongſt them that are perfect, yet not the wiſdome of this world, nor of the Princes of this world that come to nought, but we ſpeak the wiſdome of God in a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, even the hidden wiſdome which God ordained afore unto our glory. And this wiſdome and this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery the Lord hath revealed unto us, for his Names ſake, that we might be to him a praiſe, and a glory, and an honor, in walking anſwerable, and worthy of his love, in all humility and godly converſation, and we cannot partake with the world in their waies of worſhip,
<note place="margin">Epheſ: 4: 1, 2. Col: 1: 10. Epheſ: 5: 11. Jam: 3: 15. Tit: 1: 16. Rom: 1: 18.</note> which is carnal, invented intheir faln eſtate, by their carnal wiſdome, which is earthly, ſenſual, devilliſh, the root and ground of ſin, and the body, and many bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the curſed Tree is alive and not killed, and they live in ſin, and pleads for a continuance in ſin while they live on the earth, ſuch are they who profeſs God in words, but in works deny him; and ſuch are they who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115383:14"/>hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs gathering in the Saints words, the Scriptures, which were given forth from pure life and ſpirit within; theſe they gather into their unrighteous minds, and talks of God and Chriſt with their vain minds, but deceit and iniquity lodgeth in their hearts;
<note place="margin">Mat: 23: 28.</note> ſuch a Worſhip and a formal profeſſion we do deny, and againſt them do teſtifie, and cannot joyn with them, nor have fellowſhip with them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are we hated and reviled, and made a prey upon, and ſo the Scripture is fulfilled, which ſaith,
<note place="margin">Iſa: 59: 15.</note> they that depart from iniquity are become a prey to this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<note place="margin">1 Cor: 2: 9, 10</note> and this wiſdome and miſtery is hid from the worlds eye, and from their ear, they cannot ſee nor hear, nor underſtand the things of God, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that love him; but God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit, for the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God; for what man knows the things of a man, but the Spirit of a man that is in him; even ſo the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God: then all they that deny the Spirit and ſay there is no Miniſters of the Spirit now, as Prieſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcot</hi> did, knows not the things of God, but what they know naturally, (which <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks of) as bruit beaſts in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves, woe unto them for they have run in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for reward, read <hi>Iude</hi> 10, 11. And wo unto all ſuch now, that deny the Miniſtration of the Spirit, and ſaies there is no Miniſters of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit now, their knowledge is natutal and carnal, and they go in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> which is envy, and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for gifts and rewards, as the Prieſts and Pariſh Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> do, and as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcot</hi> your Teacher doth; therefore turn from him, and all ſuch, for the Lords hand is ſtretched forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115383:15"/>
            <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt were not called by Man, nor made Miniſters by the will of Man,
<note place="margin">Cal. 1.1.12 2 Cor. 5.19.</note> they were not brought up at Schools to get human learning to fit them, but they were called by God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.8. John 17.17. 1 Cor. 3.16 2 Pet. 1.20.21.</note> and made Miniſters accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, and fitted and prepared by God, and had the word of Life and Reconciliation committed to them, which was within them quick and powerfull, and wrought powerfully in their hearts; by which word they were ſanctified, and the holy Spirit was within them, and as the holy Spirit moved, ſo they ſpoke forth the Scripture, not by mans will, but by the will of God, as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt; But the Teachers of <hi>England</hi> are not ſo made nor called: For in the firſt place they are ſent to School to learn humane wiſdom in the will of man; after, they are ſent to <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and there by their cunning Craft they learn the Trade of Preaching, having men over them, and Books for that purpoſe: And when they have learned their Trade, ſerved their Apprentiſhip, then their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters give them the Commiſſion to preach, and commit unto them the Scriptures, (which were the Saints teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony within them) but theſe Prieſts have it without them, and it is neither quick nor powerful, but weak and dead, and their hearts are not ſanctified, but they plead againſt purity and holineſs of life, telling people it is impoſſible to live without ſin in this world, and they do not preach as they are moved by the Spirit, but they ſtudy in the week daies what to ſpeak, and many of them have an hour-glaſſe, and moſt of them limit themſelves to a time, and when they have uttered forth all that they have, many times tell the people, they would have enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged if the time would permit, when indeed they have no more to ſay, and ſo decieve the people, telling them they preach the word of the Lord, when it is no more but a divination of their own brain: and though they uſe ſome Texts of Scriptures, that is the greater deceit to colour their hypocriſie, and to make their ware the better to go off. But the Lord is coming to lay open their deceit, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115383:15"/>to take from them their ſtollen garments, and the ſhame of their nakedneſſe ſhall appear, and none ſhall buy their Merchandize any longer.
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.11.</note> Here you may ſee their call in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Miniſtery is contrary to the Miniſters of Chriſt, and their preaching contrary, and ſo they are to be denied.</p>
            <p>When Jeſus Chriſt ſent forth his Miniſters, he did not give them power to take tythes,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10. chap. Luke 10. chap.</note> nor any ſet or forced maintenance, but as they had recived freely, ſo they were to miniſter freely; <hi>And into what City, Town or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ye come, enquire who is worthy, and if they receive you, there ſtay and abide, eating and drinking ſuch things as they ſet before you,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10 14.</note> for the Labourer is worthy of his Hire, and the Workman is worthy of his Meat.</hi> Here he gave them power to eat and to drink with ſuch as were worthy to receive them; but they were not to do ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that did not receive them, but depart and <hi>ſhake the duſt off their feet:</hi> they were not to compell them to give them maintenance, nor meat, nor any thing elſe, but they were to miniſter freely,
<note place="margin">1 Tim 6.8.</note> and if any did freely ſet meat before them, if they would uſe their power they might eat freely. And I do not read in the the teſtimony of the Apoſtles, and Diſciples, and Miniſters of Chriſt, that they did ever receive any thing further than to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their wants and neceſſities, for having food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they were therewith content. I never read that ever any one was compelled to feed them,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.14, 15.</note> or give them maintenance, neither indeed was there any need; for the Lord whom they ſerved, ſent his power along with them, and ſuch a love was raiſed up among them, that they did receive their teſtimony, that <hi>Paul</hi> declares of ſome, that if it had been poſſible they would have plucked out their own eyes and given them to him, and it is ſo now with thoſe that receive the Truth in the love of it, nothing can be too dear for them, for they are as one anothers lives; and as they are hated by the world, and oppoſers and gainſayers of the Truth with a perfect batred, ſo they are loved by all thoſe that in ſingleneſs of heart and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs receive the Truth with a perfect love.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115383:16"/>
            <p>But the profeſſed Teachers of <hi>England</hi> are not ſo, but they have uſurped a power to take Tythes, and ſet and forced maintenances of 100, 200, or 300 pounds, or as much as they can get by the year; for they not having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived freely (as the Miniſters of Chriſt did) but have given a great deal of monies for gaining of their Art, no more can they miniſter freely. And they are more like to Heathens than to Chriſtians, they do not Chriſtian-like. <hi>Seek the Kingdom of God and the righteouſneſs of it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.32, 33. Mat. 10.11.</note> in the firſt place, neither do they according to command, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire who is worthy:</hi> For their firſt and chief thing is, what place, or ſome great fat Parſonage that is vacant, is ſought after, and enquire what the people will give, and ſo make a bargain with them for ſo much by the year, to be paid at ſuch and ſuch times, and they are very loath to preach untill they have their maintenance made ſure unto them, and yet they will tell people to believe in God, and truſt God for food for their ſouls, when they themſelves dare not truſt God for their Bellies; and they make little conſcience who they be that they take wages of, believers or not believers, ſo they can but get it, they care not: and whether they be believers or unbelievers, if they do not put into their mouthes, they preſently go about to compell them by force, which is a ſhame to hear of in a Goſpel Miniſtery, the Miniſters of the Goſpel are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ſuch practices, and what ever was received by any of the Goſpel Miniſters, it was freely miniſtred, and was to ſupply their preſent neceſſities,
<note place="margin">Phil. 4 10. to the 20.</note> and not to ſtore up and ſpend upon their luſts, as thoſe Teachers do. Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the time of the Law, when Tythes was paid to the Leviticall prieſthood, there was a ſtore houſe, and the people were to bring it freely into the ſtore houſe, and the Prieſts were not to eat alone,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.19. Deut. 14.32, 20 the end. 1 John. 10, 17, 18.</note> but the ſtrangers, and fatherleſs, and widows were to come and be filled, that there might not be a Beggar in Iſrael, and the Prieſts were to miniſter freely, a figure of Jeſus Chriſt laying down his body freely, and when any did preach for hire, it was an horrible and a filthy thing, and the Lord ſent his true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115383:16"/>to teſtifie againſt ſuch, as in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time he cryed out againſt the Idol Shepheards, <hi>that ſought gain from their Quarter,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Iſai</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>His Watchmen are blind, they are all ignorant, they are all dumb Doggs, they cannot bark, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber; yea they are greedy Doggs, which can never have enough, and they are Shepheards that cannot underſtand, they all look to their own way, every one for gain from his Quarter.</hi> And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> he was againſt the abominations in his time, and againſt the falſe Prophets and Prieſts, <hi>Jeremia</hi> the fifth chapter, <hi>The Prophets ſhall become wind, and the Word is not in them, thus ſhall it be done unto them, I will make my words in thy mouth fire, and this people wood, and it ſhall devour them; this people hath a revolting and a rebellious heart, they are revolted and gone, your iniquities have turned you away, and your ſins hath with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lden good things from you for among my people are found wicked men, they lay wait as he that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſnares, they ſet a trap, they catch men; as a Cage is full of Birds, ſo are their houſes full of deceit, therefore are they become great and waxen rich, they are waxen fat, they ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; yea, they overpaſs the deeds of the wicked, they judge not the cauſe, the curſe of the fatherleſs, yet they proſper, ſhall I not viſit for theſe things? Shall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this is? A wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and a horrible thing is committed in the Land, the Prophets propheſie falſly, &amp; the Prieſts bear rule by their means, and the people love to have it ſo, and what will ye do in the end therof?</hi> Again, read <hi>Ieremiah</hi> the 23 chapter, and there you may ſee how the Prophet was troubled becauſe of the pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>haneſſe of the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts and Prophets, <hi>My heart within me is broken becauſe of the Prophets, all my bones ſhake. I am like a drunken man, &amp;c.</hi> So both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and Prieſt are prophane, but read all the Chapter. And <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the Lords Prophet, he crys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt the falſe ſhepheards in his time, read <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 34. Chapter, <hi>Son of Man, propheſie againſt the ſhepheards of Iſrael, propheſie and ſay unto them, Thus ſaith the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God unto the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115383:17"/>of Iſrael that do feed themſelvs ſhould not the ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard feed the flock? Ye eat the fat ye cloath you with the wooll, ye kill them that are fed but ye feed not the flock, &amp;c</hi> read the chapter throughout, and there you may ſee the deceits and works of the falſe ſhepheards in thoſe dayes, and the Lords promiſe to gather his ſheep from their mouthes, and feed them himſelf upon the tops of the mountains of Iſrael. And <hi>Mica</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, who dwelt in the light of the Lord he was againſt the hireling, Prieſts in his time, as you may read in <hi>Mica</hi> 3 5. to the end of the chapter, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Prophets that make my people erre, that bite with their teeth, and cry peace, and he that doth not put into their mouthes, they even prepare warre againſt him, therefore night ſhall be unto you, that ye ſhall not have a viſion, and it ſhall be dark unto you that ye ſhall not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and the Sun ſhall go down over the Prophets, and the day ſhall be dark over them, then ſhall the Seers be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, &amp; the Diviners confounded, yea they ſhal all cover their lips, for there ſhall be no anſwer of God, the heads thereof judge for reward, and the Prieſts thereof teach for hire, and the Prophets thereof divine for money, yet will they lean upon the Lord and ſay, Is not the Lord amongſt us? no evill can come upon us. Therefore ſhall Sion for your ſakes be plowed as a Field, and Ieruſalem ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come heaps, and the Mountains of the Houſe as the High places of the Forreſt. And as Troops of Robbers wait for a man, ſo the company of Prieſts murder by the way by conſent, for they commit lewdneſs,</hi> Hoſea 69. Read <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, Here you may ſee the teſtimony of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of God againſt the hirelings and falſe ſhepheards, and greedy Teachers, and thoſe that did not miniſter free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were cryed againſt, and thoſe that did not bring their Tythes into the ſtore-houſe, they robbed God, as you may read <hi>Mal.</hi> 3 8.10 <hi>Will a man rob God, yet ye have robbed me; but ye ſay, Wherein have we robbed thee; in Tythes and Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rings: Bring ye all the Tythes into the ſtorehouſe, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there may be me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in mine houſe, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115383:17"/>prove me now herewith, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, if I will not open you the windows of Heaven, and poure you out a bleſſing, that there ſhall not be room enough to receive it.</hi> Now here you may ſee that in the time of the Law, they had a ſtore houſe, and thoſe that did not bring their Tythes thither, it is not ſaid they robbed the Prieſts, but they robbed God. But the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> that take Tythes of the peoples, have no ſtorehouſe to put the Tythes in, neither are the Strangers Widows and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs fed, but may ſterve for them, or go a begging, ſo they are not according to the law. And I do not read in all the Scriptures of the Goſpel-miniſters teſtimony, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of the believers in Chriſt, did either take Tythes or pay Tythes, much leſs to go to law, and ſue people for any outward maintenance; ſo it is manifeſt, that the Nationall and Pariſh Teachers who take tythes, and ſue thoſe at law which do not (or for conſcience ſake cannot) put into their mouthes, are neither according to law nor Goſpel. And the Miniſters of the Goſpel did teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as went in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and ran greedily after the error of <hi>Balam,</hi> for gifts and rewards, <hi>Iude</hi> 11 <hi>And ſuch falſe Tea hers, who privily ſhall bring in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hereſies denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction, &amp; through cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs ſhal they with feigned word make merchandize of the people, whoſe judgment now of a long time lingreth not, and their damnation ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbreth not,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1, 23. and <hi>a Biſhop muſt be blameleſs as the ſteward of God, not ſelf-willed, not ſoon angry, not given to wine, no ſtriker, not given to filthy lucre,</hi> Tit. 1.7. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes againſt all covetous practices, and all ſelf-ſeeking, and againſt the love of money, <hi>And</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>having food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let us be therewith content; but they that will be rich fall into temptation and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which drown men in deſtruction and perdition, for the love of mony is the root of all evill, which while ſome coveted after, they have erred from the faith, and pierced themſelves through with many ſorrows.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115383:18"/>1 Tim. 6.8, 9, 10. All theſe Scripture examples that I have here ſet down, doth condemn the ſelf ſeeking Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in <hi>England</hi> and elſwhere, who ſo much mind earthly things, and the love of money, that if they do but hear of the death of any of their fellow prieſts, if their Benefits be larger than theirs, they long to be there, and ſtrive for the place, but if the Benefice be leſs, there is no ſuch ſtriving, and this is manifeſt amongſt moſt of the Prieſts, if they can but get forty pound or threeſcore pound a year more in another place, they will leave their own hearers and go thither, and ſo love money which is the root of all evill, which the man of God was to flye theſe things, and follow after righteouſneſs, godlineſs, faith, love, patience, meekneſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaid unto his Miniſters, <hi>Be not ye called of Men Maſter,
<note place="margin">Matth. 23.8.</note> for ye have but one Maſter even Chriſt, and ye are Brethren,</hi> and they did not tranſgreſs, but did obey his commandements, for they were not called by the name of Maſter <hi>Peter,</hi> nor Maſter <hi>Paul,</hi> and the like, but <hi>Peter a Servant of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Paul a Servant of God, an Apoſtle of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.1. <hi>Titus</hi> 1 1.</p>
            <p>But thoſe who are profeſſed Teachers in <hi>England,</hi> are called of Men Maſter, contrary to Chriſts command and example of his Miniſters, and in this they are contrary to the Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt did teach the Doctrine of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and it was the chief thing and the very end for which they were given forth, as you may read <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>He that deſcended is the ſame alſo that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up farre above all heavens, that he might fill all things. And he gave ſome Apoſtles and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the body of Criſt, till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, read <hi>Col.</hi> 1.28. where <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115383:18"/>this, and for which he laboured, and others, warning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, and teaching every man in all wiſdom, that we may preſent every man perfect in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Nationall and Pariſh Maſters do deny this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of perfection, and cryes againſt thoſe that preach it as blaſphemers, &amp; they tell the people that none can be perfect in this world, and ſo they have denied the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters work, and their preaching is in vain; for if they do not perfect them here, as the true Miniſters office was, as is plain in <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. then where will they perfect them, will there be any need of their Miniſtery in Heaven? Surely no, for there ſhall be no need of mens teaching there, but the Lord alone will give them light,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.10. to the end.</note> and all ſhal know him from the leaſt to the greateſt, and ſhall walk in his preſence, and rejoyce in his love, and praiſe his holy Name, and worſhip him in the beauty of holineſs for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ever.</p>
            <p>And many other things there is which they practice, which is contrary to the practice of the holy men of God declared of in Scripture, as their ſinging of <hi>Davids</hi> conditions in Rime and Meeter, his weeping,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 6. Pſal. 119, 120. Pſal. 51 1. Pſal. 45.1. Pſal. 66.1. Pſal. 131.1.</note> his wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, his roarings and cryings, his tremblings and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, his prayers, pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſes and propheſies, theſe they give to ſimple, ignorant, proud, covetous, and prophane peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y they ſing to the praiſe and glory of God, as, <hi>O Lord I am not puft in mind, I have no ſcornfull eye, I do not exerciſe my ſelf in things that be too high,</hi> and ſuch like, when both Prieſt and people are puft in mind, and have ſcornfull eyes, they can ſcarce look one upon another they are ſo ſcornfull, and they do exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in things that be 100 high, in medling with the Saints conditions, giving their conſtructions and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and privat interpretations to the Scriptures: and thus they cauſe people to lye in the preſence of the Lord, and ſo they diſhonor God, and when they read the Pſalms, they keep on their hats, and when they ſing them they put off their has, and ſo worſhip the works of their own hands, when the Frieſt hath a Cap
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115383:19"/>or two on his head, and ſo makes a ſeeming ſhew of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and humiliation, when their hearts are full of groſſe hypocriſie and diſſimulation,
<note place="margin">Ia.m 5.13. Iſal. 35.10. Hoſea 8, 10,</note> Now whereas it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Scripture, <hi>If any be afflicted let him pray, if any be merry let him ſing Pſalms:</hi> this is owned and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but who are thoſe that are merry? truly none but the ranſomed ones of the Lord, who are redeemed from the earth, and from the bondage of corruption, theſe can truly ſing the ſongs of deliverance, and they ſhall return to <hi>Sion</hi> with joy and ſinging, and everlaſting joy ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be upon their heads. But the Songs of the wicked ſhal be turned into howling and weeping, therefore take heed how yee take the name of the Lord in vain, and ſing with your vain minds without underſtanding, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his name in vain, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.12.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe their ſprinkling Infants, and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling it an Ordinance of Chriſt, whereas neither Chriſt nor any of his Miniſters did practiſe any ſuch thing, therefore I do it deny. Now whereas Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Suffer little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God; verily I ſay unto you, whoſoever ſhall not receive the kingdom of God as a little Child, he ſhall not enter therein, and he took them up in his arms, put his hands on them and bleſſed them,</hi> Mark 10.14, 15, 16, but he did not ſprinkle water on their faces, and ſaid, he baptized them into his Church, but he ſets the child as an example for its innocency, and ſhewes that all muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as innocent as little children, for whoſoever doth not receive the kingdom of God as a little child, he ſhall not enter therein. But what example is this for any one to ſprinkle wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er on the innocent childs face, or what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage is it for a proud, covetous, heady, high minded ſinfull carnall man, to take the innocent little child which is not capable of believing, what can his prayers, or any thing he doth,
<note place="margin">John 9.31.</note> profit or advantage the innocent child. Read without prejudice, and let that of God in your conſciences judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm,</hi> and that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115383:19"/>one Baptiſm I own, which is not the putting away of the filth of the fleſh, <hi>but the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.5. 1 Pet. 3.21. Gal. 6.15. 1 Cor. 12, 13. Heb. 10 22.</note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21 For it is neither dipping or ſprinkling, or not dipping or ſprinkling that avails any thing at all, <hi>but a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for that is not the baptiſm which is outward with the water, but baptiſm is that of the Spirit, having the heart ſprinkled from an evil conſcience, &amp; the body waſhed with pure water, and as many as are baptized into Chriſt have put on Chriſt, and in Chriſt all are one, Gal.</hi> 3.27.28.</p>
            <p>And for their Sacrament which they tell people of, I deny the Scripture knows no ſuch word as <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but the Supper of the Lord I own and witneſs, which is a ſpirituall eating and drinking of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; whereby we, being many, are one bread and one body; <hi>For the cup of Bleſſing which we bleſſe is it not the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt?
<note place="margin">John 6.56.63 John 8.12.</note> the bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt?</hi> for we being many, are one bread, and one body; for we are all partakers of that one bread; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. This bread is Ieſus Chriſt the light of the world, as you may read <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.35 <hi>I am the bread of life, I am the living bread that came down from above, he that eateth of this bread ſhall live for ever, and he ſhall not hunger; and they that drink of this cup ſhall never thirſt, but it ſhall be a Well of living water ſpringing up unto eternall life,</hi> John 4.14. <hi>But I ſay, That the things which the Gentiles ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, they ſacrifice to Divels, and not to God, and I would not that ye ſhould have fellowſhip with Divels, ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of Divels, ye cannot be partakers of the Lords Table and of the Table of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.21.</p>
            <p>Now for a company of profane ſinfull people, as drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, ſwearers, lyars, ſcoffers, ſcorners, proud, lofty,
<note place="margin">John 8.44, 1 John 3 8. John 6.70.</note> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded ones, Whoremongers, Adultere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Covetous cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell oppreſſors, and the like, for theſe to meet, and eat bread &amp; wine, and call it a communion, I do it deny, to be the Communion or Table of the Lord, but the Table of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115383:20"/>Divels. Likewiſe their ſtanding praying before and after their Sermons, as they call them, and their pulpit, and their taking a Text, as they call it, and add to it the divination of their own brain, and ſpeak forth their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings and not the word of God: theſe and all or moſt things that are uſed and practiced by them in the ſteeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe or Idol-Temple, are contrary to the practice of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and they are to be turned away from, for they do not, neither ſhall they profit the people at all, for if they had ſtood in the councell of God, they ſhould have turned the people from the evill of their wayes, but they run and the Lord never ſent them, therefore they ſhal not profit the people at all.
<note place="margin">Jer. 23.32.</note> Thus I have declared and laid open their deceits and contrary walkings to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of God, and cleared the truth from their lies and ſlanders, and do deny them and all their way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<note place="margin">John 4.24. Col. 3.16. John 1.3. 1 Cor. 3.3. Phil. 3.3.</note> and do own the worſhip of God in Spirit and Truth, and the Ordinances of God in Spirit, preaching, praying, and ſinging with the Spirit, and with underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſinging with grace, and making melody in our hearts to the Lord, and Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, and the Scripture in the life and ſpirituality of them; and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of peace and glad tidings, and the word of life and reconciliation, I own and witneſs, which ſeparates from ſin and joyns to the Lord, to be one with him in Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit, where a I the children of God have union, even in the pure Spirit and love of God, and are written in one anothers hearts, not with paper and ink, but with the Spirit of the living God, and are taught of God, and worſhip him in Spirit, and rejoyceth in his love and patience for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Awake, awake, all people, awake to righteouſneſs and ſin not,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.34 Eph 5.14. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 13.12. Luke 21, 27, 28. Iſai. 4. chap. 2 Cor 4.6.</note> ariſe from your dead ſleep of carnall ſecurity, put off the works of darkneſs, and put on the armer of light, ſtand up from the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad, that Chriſt may give you light. For now is the Lord appearing, and ariſing in his mighty power for the redemption of Sion, and to put an end to ſin and finiſh tranſgreſſion, his day is dawned, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115383:20"/>the glorious light of the everlaſting Goſpel is broken forth, and ſhines in the hearts of the Lords people: the Lord is gathering his ſcattered-flock together in this his day, where they have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years been feeding upon the dry husks, and running from mountain to hill, and from hill to mountain all this cloudy dark day. Now is the Lord coming to bring back again that which was driven away, and to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt, and bring his ſheep into the fold of the the true ſhepheard, where the ſheep ſhall lie down in peace, and feed together in one fold, and the Lord alone will be the Teacher and Feeder of his Flock, and no ravenous beaſt ſhall pluck them out of his hand: for he is the good ſhepheard that will lay down his life for his ſheep,
<note place="margin">John 10 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and will not flye when the Wolfe comes to devour the Lambs, but he doth preſerve them all, and carries his lambs in his arms, and gently leads out all that are with young, all his tender babes he ſeeds with milk, and nouriſhes the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plants with the water of life, and this is the Lord bringing to paſſe in theſe our days, glory be to his name for evermore, he is fulfilling his promiſes made of old, gathering his people into union and fellowſhip with himſelf,
<note place="margin">Jer. 23: 5 6, 7.8. Iſai, 55, 3.4. Pſal. 2.1, 2. Acts 13.40, 41 John 15.18, 19.</note> where they ſhall all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce together, and be one in the everlaſting covenant of love and life in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And this makes the heathen to rage, and the world to wonder at the mighty works of the Lord our God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But it is no new thing to be reproached by the world, who knowes not God: For ſaith Chriſt, <hi>If ye were of the world, the world would love you, but becauſe I have choſen you out of the world, therefore doth it hate you.</hi> While we were of the world we were loved of the world,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.14.</note> when we were alive in the old nature, and did partake with them in their wayes of worſhip, and in their vain converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being one with them in vanity, and run with them to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and vain delights, in vain and fooliſh jeſting, and idle and vain talking, our tongues being our own, and our wild natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not being tamed, but we could do as they did, and ſpeak our own words, and think our own thoughts, and do our own works, no knowing the Croſſe of Chriſt, nor bearing his yoak, but were at eaſe in the fleſh, and in the carnall liberty, feeding upon periſhing things, and created objects, loving the world
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115383:21"/>and the things of it, and delighting in and loving the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more than the Creator. I ſay, when we were in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one with the world in moſt things, then were we eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and loved of the world, and they ſpake well of us (if we did not croſſe their wills) but even then (though we could talk of God and Chriſt, and Scriptures) we were ſtrangers from God and Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.1, 2, 3. Gal. 1.15, 16.</note> and from that pure life that the holy men of God lived in, that ſpake forth Scriptures, but then it pleaſed the Lord to manifeſt himſelf unto us, and revealed his truth within us, our underſtanding was opened by his pure light ſhining within, whereby we ſaw the deceits of the world, and their worſhip, and the hypocrifie and diſſimulation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, Prieſts and people, and that their religion was but a ſhew and ſhadow, and meer outſide ſeeming colour, and talk of words and names,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 29.13.</note> drawing neer to God with their lips, and mouthes, when their hearts were after the things of the world, and there was no life appearing, nor fruits of righteouſneſs from a true ground brought forth, but pride and ſelf-love, and covetouſneſs, every one ſeeking themſelves, and to advance themſelves by fraud and deceit, guile and hypocriſie, yea and all manner of wickedneſs we ſaw acted amongſt them, which did grieve our ſpirits, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a burden to our tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and we ſeparated from them, and could not partake with them, neither in their wayes of worſhip (as it is eſtabliſhed) nor in their converſations; but we ſeeing, in the light of the Lord,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> that they are out of the way, and their worſhip, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practices are contrary to the pure worſhip of God, and the doctrine and practices of the holy men of God decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of in Scripture,
<note place="margin">Tir. 1.16.</note> as I have ſhewed before: We ſeeing theſe things, for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake we cannot hold our peace, but in love to the ſouls of all people, do declare and teſtifie againſt the world and the unrighteouſneſs of it, and againſt the deceits and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of the Pariſh Teachers and Hirelings of theſe times, and againſt all the formall and carnall profeſſors, who in words profeſs God, but in works deny him; and for this cauſe are we hated, reviled, reproached, beaten, whipped, ſtocked, ſtoned, and ſent up and down the Countrey as Vagabonds, and abuſed and ſent to priſon, and this is manifeſt at this day in <hi>England,</hi> the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115383:21"/>war is begun already betwixt the Beaſt and the Lamb, but the Lamb ſhal get the victory; though all joyn hand in hand againſt the innocent, it ſhall all be in vain, they ſhall not prevail,
<note place="margin">Rev. 17.14. Mica 4.1, 2. Mat. 5.10, 11, 12. John 16.20, 21. Pſal. 30.35. 2 Pet. 1.19. Rev. 21.23 24 Heb. 11.26.</note> but the Lord over all ſhall be exalted, and his kingdom ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, and the Mountain of the Houſe of the Lord ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the mountains, and it ſhall be ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lted above the Hills, and people ſhall flow unto it, and though we now be perſecuted and hated, and troubled on every ſide, yet it ſhall not be long, for the Lord will plead the cauſe of the innocent, and though ſorrow and trouble may endure for a night, yet joy will come in the morning, when the glorious day of the Lord doth dawn within, and the day-ſtar doth ariſe in the heart, then ſhall darkneſs be expelled, and all the children of the Lord ſhall walk in the light of the Lord, and rejoyce in his preſence, and reproaches to us are great riches, for we know it is our portion from the worldly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall profeſſors, thoſe who have the name and form of godlineſs, but are not in the life, they are and were ever found perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the life where ever it did appear. As in the time of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> adminiſtration, when the Lord did appear darkly as it were, under types and ſhadowes,
<note place="margin">Mar. 23.31. John 5.35. John 1.14.</note> and the people for a time were held under that adminiſtration. And in the times of the Prophets more light was diſcovered, and they ſaw through the ſhadows, and declared againſt them, and thoſe who were in the types and ſhadows perſecuted the Prophets. The Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were untill <hi>Iohn,</hi> and amongſt all that were born of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, there was not a greater than <hi>Iohn,</hi> for he was a burning and a ſhining light, and this was a greater light than the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, yet the leaſt in the kingdom is greater than <hi>Iohn.</hi> And in the admiſtration of the Goſpel, when the fulneſs of time was come, when Chriſt was manifeſt in the fleſh, who was the end of the Law and the Prophets. Thoſe who had the form of the Law, and the Prophets words,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26 3.4, Mark 15 15. Col. 1.20.21, 22, 23.</note> they perſecuted Chriſt the life of the Law and the Prophets, as many do now in theſe our days, who have got the words of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and cryes up names and words, as the Ordinances of Chriſt, and the Church of Chriſt, and the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, are perſecuting the appearance of Chriſt and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115383:22"/>his life that is now manifeſt in his people as it was in former times under the Law, thoſe that multiplied their Sacrifices and burnt offerings, but their hearts were far off, and the bond of iniquity was not broken, nor the oppreſſed ſet free, but they lived in their ſins, and ſo were teſtified againſt by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, as thou mayſt read, <hi>Iſaia</hi> chapter 1. <hi>The Ox knoweth his Owner, and the Aſſe his maſters Crib, but Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not conſider, a ſinfull Nation, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple laden with iniquity, a ſeed of evill doers, children that are corrupters, they have forſaken the Lord, they have provoked the holy one of Iſrael to anger, they have gone away backward: The whole head is ſick, and the whole heart faint, from the ſole of the foot even unto the head, there is no ſoundneſs in it, but wounds &amp; bruiſes, and putrifying ſoars, they have not bin cloſed, neither bound up, neither mollified with oyntment. To what purpoſe is the multitude of your ſacrifices unto me, ſaith the Lord, I am full of the burnt offerings of Rams, and the fat of fed beaſts, and I delight not in the blood of Bullocks or of Lambs, or of he Goats, when you come before me, who hath required this at your hands? Bring no more vain Oblations, Incenſe is an abomination unto me, the New Moon; and Sabbaths, the calling of Aſſemblies, I cannot away with, it is iniquity even the ſolemn meeting: your New Moons and your appointed Feaſts my ſoul hateth, they are a trouble to me, I am weary to hear them, and when you ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you, when yee make many prayers I will not hear, your hands are full of blood, waſh ye make you clean, put away the evill of your doings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to do evill, learn to do well, ſeek judgement, relieve the oppreſſed, judge the Fatherleſs, and plead for the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now you people of all ſorts, who makes a profeſſion of God, and call together Aſſemblies, examine your ſelves truly, and ſee if you be not in the condition of thoſe whom the prophet cryes againſt:
<note place="margin">Mat 7.22, 23.</note> Are you not revolted from the Lord? Are you not a ſinfull people, laden with iniquity, a ſeed of ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll doers? Have not you provoked the Lord to anger by your unrighteous walking? Are not you corrupted with ſin from the ſole of the foot even to the head? Can you deny theſe things? Nay, I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115383:22"/>have heard ſome of you confeſſe this in words. Then to what purpoſe is your Sabbaths and your ſolemn meetings, as your calling of Aſſemblies, your dayes of humiliation, as you call them, and your Lecture dayes, and your long prayers, who hath required theſe things at your hands? It is all bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom to the Lord, and he cannot away with it; it is in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, even your ſolemn meetings, and your prayers are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Lord will not hear them, for your hands are full of blood, you are full of envy.
<note place="margin">Mat. 23 14. Deut. 32.29. Iſal. 47.7, 8, 9 Luke 11.49.</note> Oh when will yee lay theſe things to heart, and conſider and depart from iniquity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the oppreſſed, and undo the heavy burdens, and plead the cauſe of the innocent, and not ſend to priſon nor perſecute the his innocent ſervants: It is not your ſaying Lord, Lord, nor your hypocriticall prayers, nor outſide holineſſe that will avail you, nor cover your nakedneſs in the day of the Lord; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ceaſe from your ſin and your ungodlineſs, and learn the wayes of righteouſneſs, that your ſouls may live, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>Again, read <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66.1, 2, 3. There you may ſee how the Prophet declared againſt the Temple, and the Sacrifices, which were outward, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Heaven is my Throne, and the Earth is my Footſtool, where is the Houſe that ye build unto me? and where is the place of my reſt?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He that kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth an Ox is as if he ſlew a Man, he that ſacrificeth a Lamb, as if he cut off a Dogs neck, he that offereth an Oblation as if he offered Swines blood, he that burneth Incenſe as if he bleſſed an Idoll; yea, they have choſen their own wayes, and their ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in their abominations.</hi> Conſider and let this judge you, who have forſaken the wayes of the Lord, and have choſen your own wayes, and delights in your abominations,
<note place="margin">Mat. 15.8, 9,</note> the Lord wall plead with you. And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> cryed againſt thoſe that truſted in lying words, that lived in oppreſſion and ſin. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts the God of Iſrael, Amend your lives and your doings, and I will cauſe you to dwell in this, Truſt yee not in lying words, ſaying, The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe: For if ye through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amend your wayes and your doings, if ye throughly execute judgment between a man and his Neighbour, if ye oppreſs not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115383:23"/>the ſtranger, the Fatherleſs and the widow, and ſhed not innocent blood, then will I cauſe you to dwell in this place,</hi> Jer. 7.3, 4, 5, 6,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.14. 1 Cor, 1.30. Mat. 7.12.</note> 7. Let this judge you all that truſt in lying words, crying the Church of Chriſt, and the Ordinance of Chriſt, and the Miniſtery of the Goſpel, and ſo makes a great noiſe and talk of words, for theſe things are not known to you while you live in the old nature; but if yee throughly amend your wayes, and put off the Old man with his deeds, and put on the New man Chriſt-Jeſus, then ſhall the Church of Chriſt be known, and all the ordinances of Chriſt lived in, in the life and power of them, but not while you live in ſin.</p>
            <p>And again,
<note place="margin">Mica. 66.7, 8.</note> the Prophet <hi>Mica</hi> he ſaw through the Figures, and ſaw the upright and juſt life which the Lord required, as you may read in <hi>Mica</hi> 6.6, 7, 8. <hi>Wherewith ſhall I come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and bow my ſelf before the high God? Shall I come before him with burnt offerings, with Calves of a year old? Will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſands of Rams, or with ten thouſand of Rivers of Oyl? Shall I give my firſt born for my tranſgreſſion, the fruit of my body for the ſin of my ſoul? He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, and what doth the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of thee but to do juſtly, and love mercy, and towalk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God.</hi> Theſe examples. I bring, that you may ſee how the Lord did ſend his Servants and Prophets to cry againſt deceit and hypocriſie, and againſt thoſe that made a profeſſion, but were out of the life and poſſeſſion. And thoſe whom the Lord thus ſent, they were hated by thoſe whom they decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt in the time of their teſtimony: And afterward ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generation comes, and cryes up their words, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in the time of their propheſie, they were hated, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their death another generation gets their words, but ſtill perſecuteth alike. And this was manifeſt in the dayes of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Heb. 8.1.</note> when he was manifeſt in the Fleſh, who was the ſubſtance of <hi>Moſes</hi> Types, and the end and life of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; he was hated by the Jewes, Chief Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſees, who had gotten the words, and painted themſelves with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets words, and cryed up the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, building their Tombs, and garniſhing the Sepulchers of the Righteous, and condemned their forefathers for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115383:23"/>of the prophets; and yet theſe were them that crucified the Son of God,
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.2.</note> who was the life and ſubſtance of thoſe things which they upheld, which were outward and typicall, but though they made a fair ſhew and large profeſſion, and were zealous for their Sabbath, and ſtrict in their obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet they lived in their ſins, and Chriſt ſaw their hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and cryes wo unto them, as you may read <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſies hypocrites, for ye make clean the outſide of the Cup and of the Platter, but within they are full of extorſion and exceſſe. Thou blind Phariſee, cleanſe firſt that which is wihin the Cup and Platter, that the outſide may be clean alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees hypocrites, for ye are like unto whited Sepulchers, which indeed appear beautiful outward,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.3, 4. &amp; 27, 26 Acts 2.41. Acts 7.48, 49. to the end.</note> but are within full of dead mens bones and all uncleaneſs: Even ſo ye alſo outwardly appear righteous unto men, but within ye are full of hypocriſie and iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees hypocrites, becauſe ye build the Tombs of the Prophets, and garniſh the Sepulchers of the righteous, and ſay, If we had lived in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the Prophets; wherefore ye be witneſſes unto your ſelves that ye are the children of them that killed the Prophets: Fill ye up then the meaſure of your Fathers. Ye Serpents, ye generation of vipers, how have ye eſcaped the damnation of Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you may ſee that Chriſt deals plainly with them, and doth not wink at ſin, but reproves them ſharply: And it was no railing, as ſome call it now: for he ſaw their deceit, and they were in rage and envy againſt him, and the Chiefe Prieſts and Rulers took counſell againſt him, and crucified him; but notwithſtanding all this, did not put a ſtop to the work of the Lord, but he appeared again unto his Diſciples, and filled them with his Spirit of power, and they went and preached the Goſpel, and cryed down the Temple-worſhip, and the Ceremonies of the Law; and for this they were hated,
<note place="margin">Acts 8.2, 3.</note> and perſecuted, and ſome were ſtoned to death by ſuch as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the Temple and the outward commands, and <hi>Saul</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt made havock of the Church, and perſecuted
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115383:24"/>them from Citie to Citie. And thus in the Apoſtles time they were perſecuted by ſuch as had the form of godlineſs, but were ſtrangers to the power and life of godlineſs. But I do not read in all the Scriptures that ever the Chriſtians did perſecute any who were Chriſtians indeed; ſo that perſecution is a mark of the Beaſt, and of Antichriſt, and it was ever blind. After the Apoſtles time many there was that got the form of truth,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1, 2 3, 4 5, 6, 7, 8, 1 John 2, 18.</note> and in the Apoſtles times the Doctrine of Antichriſt crept in, which now hath over-ſpread a great part of the world, and darkneſs hath long been over all Nations; and though ſome have born the name of Chriſtians, yet far they are from the Chriſtians life, and theſe now in our age have gotten the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and as thoſe in the days of Chriſt had gotten the form of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets words, ſo theſe have gotten the form of Chriſt &amp; the Apoſtles words, but are far from Chriſt and the Apoſtles life: and as they then in that generation did did condemn their fore fathers for killing the Prophets,
<note place="margin">Luke 11.47, 48.</note> and yet did perſecute Chriſt the Life, ſo theſe now in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration do condemn their fore fathers the Jewes for crucifying of Chriſt, and yet are found in rage and malice, and perſecution againſt the appearance of Chriſt in Spirit in his Saints now: yea thoſe who have been looked upon as godly men, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and prayed for the pouring forth of the Spirit upon ſons and upon daughters, and that the Lord would teach his people himſelf by his Spirit thoſe things have been ſpoken of and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in this generation by Prieſts and People. And now when the day is come, and the Lord hath poured forth his Spirit upon Sons and Daughters, yet becauſe it is not in their way, and in their time, and according to their expectation, therefore they cry out, and perſecute, and revile and ſpeak againſt the Lords light and appearance within, as it was formerly by the enemies and oppoſers of Truth, and theſe cry out againſt freedom from ſin, and againſt perfection, as a blaſphemous Doctrine; but it is that which the Lord is bringing to paſs,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.16, 17, 18. Rev. 21.27. 1 Cor. 6.9, 10.</note> gathering his people into his everlaſting Covenant, where ſin and iniquity enters not, but is for ever ſhut out of the Kingdome and Covenant of God. For theſe Teachers and People in theſe our dayes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115383:24"/>who cry up and profeſſe Chriſt without, and a Church and a worſhip without, and a Law and Light, and Word without, and their Rule and Ordinances without, and their Teachers and all other things without, are but in in the ſtate and condition, (nay they are ſhort) of thoſe who upheld the Temple-worſhip and Ceremonies of the Law, which made nothing perfect, though there was in the firſt covenant Ordinances of Divine Service, and a worldly Sanctuary: For there was a Tabernacle made, the firſt wherein was the Candleſtick, and the Table, and the Shew-Bread, which is called the Sanctuary; and after the ſecond veil the Tabernacle, which is called the Holieſt of all: And other things as you may read, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. the holy Ghoſt thus ſignifying, that the way into the Holieſt of all, was not yet made manifeſt while as the firſt Tabernacle was yet ſtanding, which was a figure for the time then preſent, in which were offered both Gifts &amp; Sacrifices, that could not make him that did the Service perfect as pertaining to the conſcience, which ſtood onely in meats and drinks, and divers waſhings and carnall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances impoſed on them untill the time of reformation; and in that covenant and admin ſtration there was an outward Temple, and a Law, and Sabbath, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion without, and Prieſts that did offer up Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Burnt Offerings, whoſe lips were to preſerve knowledge; but nevertheleſs there was a diſanulling of all theſe things for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs thereof,
<note place="margin">Heb: 7: 18, 19. Heb: 10.1. Heb. 8.7, 8. to the end.</note> for the Law made nothing perfect but the bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in of a better hope, by the which we draw nigh unto God, and all theſe things were but as Types and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of better things to come, and of a new Covenant, in which ſin and iniquity ſhall be done away: For if that firſt covenant had been faultleſs, then ſhould no place have been ſound for the ſecond, for finding fault with them he ſaith, <hi>Behold the dayes come ſaith the Lord, that I will make a new Covenent with the Houſe of Iſrael and with the Houſe of Judab not according to the Covenant that I made with their Fathers in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y when I took them by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115383:25"/>the hand to lead them out of the Land of Egypt, for they continued not in my Covenant, and I regarded them not, ſaith the Lord, for this is the Covenant that I will make with the Houſe of Iſrael after thoſe days, ſaith the Lord I will wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e my Law in their hearts, and put my Spirit in their inward parts, and I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a people, and they ſhall not teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord; for all ſhall knew me from the leaſt to the greateſt, for I will be merciful to their unrighteouſneſs, &amp; their ſins and iniquities I will remember no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the new Covenant propheſied of the dayes of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 4.21 A &amp;s 2.16, 17 Exod. 34.1. Exod. 31: 14, 15, 16, Exod: 40: 12, 13. 1 Chron: 17.12. Gen. 17.10, Exod. 37.29. 2 Cor. 3.3, 1 Cor. 3.16, 17, Rom. 2: 28, 29. Matth. 12.8, 1 Cor. 10.1, 2, 3, 4. Mat. 10.28, 29, 1 Iohn 2, 27. Heb: 4, 12, Rom: 10.8. 1 Cor: 6.11, Heb. 9: 13, 14</note> and was ſulfilled in the days of Chriſt &amp; the Apoſtles, and is now fulfilled, and fulfilling, in theſe our dayes; and as in the old covenant the Law without, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Tables of Stone, and the Sabbath was without, and the Prieſts were without, whoſe lipps were to preſerve knowledg; and the Temple was withont, circumciſion and many other things were without, and the anointing Oyl, theſe things were outward, but did not make the comers thereunto perfect as pertaining to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they did but cleanſe the outſide. But in the new Covenant the life and ſubſtance is within: the Law is written in the Tables of the Heart, and the Spirit is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to teach them; and their Bodies are the Temple of God, and Circumciſion of the Heart with the Spirit, and the Sabbath (or reſt) is witneſſed, which is Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Reſt and the Rock and Refuge to flye unto, and whoſoever doth come unto him, and take his yoak upon them, and learn of him, they ſhall find reſt to their ſouls: And the Anointing is within, and the Word of Life and Reconciliation, which is as a ſharp Sword to cut down all ſin and all the luſts of the fleſh. This word is within, nigh in the heart, and in the mouth, and by this Word of Life and power within, were the Saints and holy men of God purified and cleanſed, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences purged from dead workes, and were created a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, to ſerve God in the new life of Righteouſneſs, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115383:25"/>it is the work of God within that doth make perfect from ſin,
<note place="margin">Eph: 2.10: Rom: 8.2: 2 Pet. 1.19, 21;</note> even the law of the Spirit of Life that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, that made him free from the law of Sin and Death: And from this Word and Spirit of Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, was all the Scriptures given forth, and all words or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings that are ſpoken or written, are to bring to the Word and Spirit within: For whatſoever was written or ſpoken by <hi>Moſes</hi> or by the Prophets, Chriſt or the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<note place="margin">John 4.24 1 John 1, 7,</note> being ſpoken and written from the Spirit and Light within, they are all to bring out of all Shadowes and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures,
<note place="margin">Luke 17.20, Col: 2, 20, 21, 22. Heb: 9.9, 10 Heb. 10.1 Luke 15.16, Iſaiah 55.2, Luke 24.5, Jer. 2.13. Ezek: 3 4, 5, 6, Mica 6 6.14 Mat 7, 22, 23. Mal: 3, 5, John 3.17, 20</note> and carnall Obſervations to the worſhip of God within in the Spirit, where the Saints union and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is in the Spirit and Light within. So all you, both Prieſts and People, in this generation, who are ſeeking the kingdom in your Obſervations, whoſe worſhip and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and Light, and Word, and Rule, and other things, are without. I ſay unto you, your worſhip is but carnall, and all that which you practiſe it doth not cleanſe you, nor make you perfect; you are but feeding upon the husks, you are ſpending your labour for that which doth not ſatisfie, and ſpending your money for the which is not bread, you are ſeeking the living amongſt the dead, you are ſeeking water among the broken Ciſterns that will hold no water, you are as the woman that ſought the loſt Groat without, you are as ſheep without a Shepheard, ſcattered upon the mountains, but find no reſt, you are hungry but are not ſatisfied: Nay, I know there is a cry within you for purity and holineſs of life, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all your talking, and your obſervations, your preaching and your praying, you are condemned in your ſelves for your unrighteous walking: and this is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the world, becauſe light is come into the world, and yet men love darkneſs better than light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds be evill.</p>
            <p>Therefore take heed of deſpiſing the light within,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1, 19, John 1.5. John 8, 12, 1 John 3, 5,</note> but take heed to, and mind the light that ſhines in your dark hearts, and reproves you for your ſin, that out of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion ye may come and follow Chriſt in the light,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115383:26"/>which whoſoever follows, ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life;
<note place="margin">John 14.6. Acts 4.12. John 1.9.</note> for God is light, and he out of his love hath given his Son for a covenant of light unto the people to lead them out of darkneſs, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them from ſin, and to joyn them to the Lord, and there is no way to life but by the Son of God, there is no other name under heaven given by which any man can be ſaved, than by the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who is the light of the world, and doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world, and this light is true and pure, and teſtifies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin and evill, though you act ſin never ſo cloſely, that none in the world can accuſe you, yet this light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you doth ſtand a witneſſe againſt you, &amp; condemn you, and though you may alter and change your wayes, and be toſſed to and fro by mens changeable Doctrines, yet this light of Chriſt within you doth never change, but doth reprove you for ſin and evill, &amp; make manifeſt darkneſs &amp; the deeds of darkneſs,
<note place="margin">Eph, 5.13.</note> that is the light; or all things that are reproved are made manifeſt by the light; whatſoever makes manifeſt is light, that which tels you that lying is a ſin, and ſwearing is a ſin, and whoredom &amp; drunkenneſs, and pride and covetouſneſs, that which doth reprove you when you act any evill, that is the light that I ſpeak of, and do direct your minds unto, to wait upon God in the light for teaching, and power over ſin, and as you have many years been ſeeking without, and talking of Chriſt and Saviour without, but have not found peace nor free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but are alive in your ſins, and laden with iniquity; ſo now turn in your minds to the light of Chriſt, and there wait for the appearance of Chriſt in you,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.6, 7, Col: 1.27, 2 Cor: 4.10, 11. 1 John 3.8, 1 John 5.12, 29. 1 Cor. 3.17. Eph. 3.17. Rom. 8.10,</note> and for his life and power to be made manifeſt in your mortall bodies to kill and ſlay ſin, and to purifie your bearts, that your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide may be clean by the pure power and life of Chriſt within, that ſo your bodies may be Temples of God holy and pure, that God, who is Light may dwell within you; and Chriſt Jeſus, who is light, may appeare within you: For he is not known in power to kill and deſtroy the workes of the Divell but as he is known within, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115383:26"/>where he is witneſſed come in the fleſh, there is peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in him; but while you live in your ſins there is no peace; and as you love that little light within you,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13, 5, Iohn 14, 27. Iſal. 48.22. Mat. 13.31, 32 1 Iohn 2.27, Iohn 3.19, 20, 21. 1 Tim: 3.9. Ezra 3.19. Pſalm 1.6</note> which at firſt is but ſmall like a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, but wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in patience, and bringing your deeds to it to be tried by it, it will grow and ſpring in you, and fill your hearts with joy, and teach you continually; but if you hate this light, and run to men for teaching, and live in your old nature, where the curſe and wrath is, this light will be your condemnation, and truly this I ſay unto you, That if ever you own God, or his truth as it is in Chriſt Jeſus; or if ever you own a good conſcience, where the myſtery of faith is held, you muſt own this light to be your guide and teacher; ſo take warning in your life time, and let not the love of God be tendered to you in vain, leſt you periſh in your ſins.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written in love to your Souls by a Labourer in the Lords Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, known to the world by the name of <hi>Alexander Parker.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115383:27"/>
            <head>To all thoſe who are ſeparated from the Worlds publick Worſhip (as it is called) and for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake cannot joyn with them.</head>
            <p>DEarly beloved friends, you whoſe hearts are touched, and underſtandings opened with the light of Jeſus, whereby you are come to ſee the deadneſs and emptineſs of all the Formall and Carnall Worſhips, and profeſſion, that ſtands in mans will, gathered in by the ſtrength of the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the ſubtile Serpent, whoſe head is not bruiſed, but doth rule as King in faln Man, and leads him captive at his will to do his luſts: Such are thoſe who profeſſe God in words, but in works deny him, drawing nigh unto him with their lips and mouthes, crying Lord, Lord, but their hearts are far off, the Divell he keeps poſſeſſion there, and ſits as King, and they are his ſlaves who live in envy, wrath and malice, pride, luſt, covetouſneſſe, lying, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, railing and reviling, and the like. Such beares the mark of their father the Divel, who hath begotten them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his image and likeneſſe, and their prayers and and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſices are abomination, and ſtinks in the noſtrils of the pure God, and they do not, neither ſhall they profit the people at all, but leads them captive laden with ſin, and led away with divers luſts, ever learning, but never come to the true knowledge of God, as it is plainly manifeſt to the children of light. And theſe things (friends) the Lord hath let you ſee, and turned you from them and their carnall worſhips. Now wait in patience upon the Lord in his light, that you may receive his power and word of life and reconciliation in your hearts, to ſeparate you from all ſin and unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. That as the ſeparation is made without in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo the ſeparation may be made within by the pure po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, that your hearts may be purified, and your conſciences purged from all ſin, and your Bodies made Temples holy and pure for the Lord God to dwell in, that you may worſhip God in Spirit in his holy Temple, and be taught of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115383:27"/>him in Spirit according as he hath promiſed, and according as you have been directed by his ſervants and faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſo wait and walk with the loyns of your minds girt up, and ſtayed upon the Lord, that his living Word may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in you, and quicken your mort all bodies, and raiſe you up from death and dead works, to ſerve and worſhip God in the new life, that you may truly witneſſe Jeſus to be your Teacher and Feeder. If you ſhould never behold the Face of man more, this is that which I and and all my friends do wait for, that all of you may eat your own bread, &amp; have oyl in your own veſſels, for the time draweth nigh that all who have not oyl in their veſſels will be ſhut out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: It will then be in vain to beg or buy from others. Therefore beloved, as you and many others have long been looking without, and ſeeking the kingdom of God in Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations without, and talking of a Chriſt and a Saviour without, but no peace nor ſalvation was found there. Now return home, and ſeek the loſt groat in your own houſe, and wait in the light for the glorious appearance of Chriſt in you, that his life and power may be manifeſt in you to ſave you from your ſins. So as branches abide in the vine Chriſt Jeſus, that you may be fruitfull and abound in love, and all the gifts of God. This I write unto you by way of remembrance, to ſtir up your pure minds, that you may be kept watchfull and diligent, waiting in patience untill the work of the Lord be perfected in you. So the Lord God of power breath forth his Spirit upon you, and enrich you with his ſpirituall bleſſings, that you may abound in all good things, and be kept blameleſſe and harmleſſe amongst this wicked and untoward generation of men, ſtanding faithfull to the Lord in all things, that you may finiſh your courſe with joy, and be crowned with glory, and reign with the Lord God and the Lamb, and praiſe his holy Name, and worſhip him in the beauty of his Holineſſe for every and ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
